<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xs="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns:type="application/tei+xml" xml:id="COM-00007">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Foreign Trade</title>
            <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/search?query=local.names+all+%22Wolfgang Klenner%22">
               <name type="person">Wolfgang Klenner</name>
               <idno type="ORCID"/>
               <idno type="ISNI"/>
            </author>
            <funder ref="placeholder"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>BRILL</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Leiden | Boston</pubPlace>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title level="m"/></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Asian Studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css" schemeVersion="3.0"/>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="italic">font:italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="bold">font:bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="underline">font:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="subscript">font:subscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="superscript">font:superscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallcaps">font:smallcaps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20121018" status="first-print">Print publication</change>
         <change when="20081110" status="first-online"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>1. Developments through 1949</head>
            <p>Until the beginning of the 19th century, China's foreign trade was in the hands of Chinese merchants and officials and their trading partners from Asia, increasingly also from Europe. Data on the volume and structure of foreign trade from that era is sparse. It was certainly not free trade in the narrower sense of the term. Foreign trade was viewed much more as a form of the tribute trade (<ref target="COM-00141">tributary system</ref>) and lay under government control. All the same, people appear to have paid heed to market opportunities. For example, export goods like <ref target="SIM-00214">silk</ref> and porcelain (<ref target="SIM-00119">ceramics</ref>), which were favored overseas and hence could be sold for a higher price, took up a greater share of China's exports. This gradually led to a relatively advantageous trade integration of the entire East and Southeast Asian region.</p>
            <p>The sectoral and regional variety in trade was drastically reduced when the European powers divided East and Southeast Asia into spheres of influence at the beginning of the 19th century and bound "their" respective regions to them. Not only were bilateral trade structures established, which served unilateral interests, even the customary interregional Asian trade was eliminated, since it represented trade among different spheres of influence. At the beginning of the 19th century, opium grown in India acquired increasing importance. In the hands of British merchants trading in China, opium was increasingly used as a medium of exchange in place of silver (<ref target="SIM-00179">Opium Wars</ref>); estimates for 1830 place the share of opium imports at about 60% of total imports. Not only did British trading houses benefit from the opium trade, so did Chinese merchants as well as certain groups within the bureaucracy. Opium trade was a shared interest created by British dominance that significantly impacted the structure and scope of foreign trade and which in the Guangdong region was called the "Canton system". Noteworthy changes to import structures followed in the late 19th century, as China increasingly imported cotton textiles as well as kerosene for lighting. Among China's exports, <ref target="SIM-00239">tea</ref> and silk originally dominated, with a share of about 90% in 1868. By the end of the 19th century, exports had broadened and cotton, vegetable oils, pig bristles, skins, furs, etc. were also sold on the world market. At the same time, however, China was hardly in a position to manufacture any more refined products.</p>
            <p>At the beginning of the 20th century, in order to strengthen mobilizing industrialization efforts, industrial raw materials were imported, as were equipment and machines, especially textile machines. Meanwhile, China exported textiles and certain mining products in significantly greater quantity than before. Nonetheless, even then China was still generally confronted with a trade deficit that at times amounted to more than half of its exports. This deficit was financed at first with metal-based currency and then increasingly through foreign credit. In the 1930s, China's foreign trade stagnated as a result of the global depression, and the chaos of war later prevented a quick recovery.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2. Developments 1949-1978</head>
            <p>After the establishment of the People's Republic, CCP cadres came to power, who used foreign trade to serve development policy goals. The prerequisite for the fact that politics and the state made foreign trade decisions rather than merchants' private economic calculations was brought about by the creation of a special foreign trade bureaucracy (<ref target="COM-00010">foreign economic policy</ref>). China's import structures soon changed fundamentally. Imports were to serve <ref target="COM-00064">industrialization</ref> first and foremost. Accordingly, machines, equipment, chemicals, metals, and minerals composed the lion's share of imports. Foreign luxury goods were not to be imported, although basic foodstuffs could be in order to ensure sustenance for the populace, especially in the coastal cities. Due to China's underdeveloped transport infrastructure, it was easier to supply the coastal cities through deliveries from overseas than from the interior. For a long time, exports remained overwhelmingly products of primary industries with low added value, because China did not have the capacity in the short term to transform production and broaden the spectrum of goods destined for the world market.</p>
            <p>It may be assumed that in principle China was interested in a broad, regional diversification of its foreign trade in order to avoid dependence on powerful foreign trade partners. This turned out to be impossible, however, because the US trade embargo prevented Western businesses from intensifying their trade contacts with China. Only the Soviet Union and other command-economy countries supported China's socialist development and supplied industrial equipment among other things. Because of the difficulties involved in converting Rubles and Yuan into Western currencies, it is hard to quantify the trade flow between China and the Soviet bloc in a Western currency. Only estimates exist, for example, placing the Soviet-Chinese trade between 1950 and 1959 at about $2 billion. A portion of the imports at that time were financed through credit - estimated at $1.4 billion between 1950 and 1959 - the repayment of which was primarily accomplished through the delivery of raw materials and agricultural products. Based on the experience of the 18th and 19th centuries, however, China avoided foreign trade deficits, which all to often were bound with dependence on foreign trade partners. The Chinese thought it was possible, however, to politically and economically justify raising investments beyond the then still relatively low domestic savings rate through debt to the ideological like-minded command-economy countries.</p>
            <p>It is scarcely possible to make statements regarding the advantages and disadvantages to China that grew out of the trade with the Soviet bloc at that time, because of the arbitrary nature of the prices set for the exchanged goods. It is nevertheless incontrovertible that through this trade China was put in a position to develop the heavy industry sector so important to the further industrialization of the country. The average yearly growth rate of China's heavy industry between 1952 and 1959 was about 25%. China gained distant access to relatively modern technologies and received practical instruction in the organization of complex work processes. In this way, increases in production and productivity were unleashed that can be equated with the "big push" effect described by development theory.</p>
            <p>By the time party cadres pressed specialists in economic administration and big business into the service of the <ref target="SIM-00084">Great Leap Forward</ref> policy, the Soviet Union was no longer willing to support China's economic development. In addition, differences of opinion over fundamental ideological questions soon contributed to a drastic reduction of bilateral economic relations. In 1962, for example, the trade volume of the two countries was only about $200 million. The risks accompanying foreign debt became painfully clear. To minimize these risks, debts were paid with deliveries of goods, despite catastrophic harvest failure in the early 1960s. Under such conditions the import of equipment and machines was hardly possible.</p>
            <p>In the following years, China's economy consolidated. Export revenues were increasingly attained. Henceforth the emphasis was on aligning imports with foreign exchange revenues and at the same time constructing the broadest possible foreign trade relations at the regional level. Primarily equipment was imported, although no longer mainly for heavy industry, as in the 1950s, but rather for the fertilizer and petrochemical industries. The impending economic dynamic, however, was interrupted by the <ref target="COM-00076">Cultural Revolution</ref>.</p>
            <p>After the Cultural Revolution, economic development was once again placed at the center of political efforts. This was accompanied by an expansion of imports. Agricultural products such as rice, soybeans, fruits, meat, raw animal products, silk, natural fibers, tea, tobacco, and so forth continued to predominate among exports, with a share of about one third of the total exports in 1978. During the same period, exports of textiles and clothing contributed to about a quarter of China's export revenues. Early on such imports already comprised a relatively stable component of Chinese exports and suppressed strong swings in foreign exchange revenues, which would otherwise have appeared during crisis years as a result of poor agricultural returns. Other noteworthy export revenues were produced by the fuel sector, especially the petroleum industry, which accounted for about a tenth of the foreign exchange revenue at the end of the 1970s. Thanks to rising foreign exchange revenues, the import of modern equipment and facilities gained importance once again. In addition, imports of rolled-steel products and nonferrous metals braced China's industrialization. In 1978, these metals accounted for nearly a quarter of the value of all imports. The import of agricultural products like wheat, sugar, oleaginous crops, cotton, etc. sank proportionately. Their share of imports, which during crisis years was extraordinarily high - in the early 1960s for example it was about 50% - fell to about 20%.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. Developments since 1978</head>
            <p>In the course of the reforms introduced since 1978, businesses first gained greater autonomy in the domestic economy. Later, the Chinese abandoned enforcing the state monopoly on foreign trade and foreign exchange. The authority to make decisions regarding the import and export of goods and services as well as capital was increasingly delegated, initially to entrepreneurially structured organizations with regional administrative units and later to individual firms as well. Moreover, two formerly authoritative principles of foreign trade policy were abandoned. Previously, import volumes had been matched to the respective foreign exchange revenue earned through exports. The import of modern equipment and facilities was accordingly always limited, on the one hand by the given foreign exchange revenue and on the other by the minimum import volume required for economically essential foreign exchange rates. Hence increases in production and especially advances in productivity depended heavily on highly erratic export revenues. In order to uncouple imports in general and equipment imports in particular from the development of export revenues, the Chinese leadership decided to conduct imports generally on a credit basis. The renunciation of the principle of not allowing private foreign enterprises to operate in Chinese territory had a similar goal. Direct <ref target="SIM-00016">foreign investment</ref> in the forms of <ref target="SIM-00113">joint ventures</ref>, foreign subsidiaries, mergers, acquisitions, and so forth were thus permitted. Transactions of this nature had an advantage over importing equipment and facilities on a cash or credit basis because in addition to the acquisition of technological knowledge and management know-how, access to foreign markets was facilitated. In this way, the import of equipment and facilities - which was to be expanded in order to assist in the transition from intensive to extensive growth - no longer possessed the buffering function which had effectively fallen to such imports in the past, at least during some phases of development. Instead, such imports became a strategic element of China's new growth and foreign trade strategies.</p>
            <p>As a result of this new policy, the volume of imports and exports changed drastically compared to previous decades, as did the commodity range and regional structure of foreign trade. Parallel to developments in economically successful neighboring countries that were integrated in the global market can easily be shown. In the period from 1981 to 1986, the foreign trade volume had a yearly growth rate of 13.5% (imports 12.9%, exports 14.2%). In absolute figures, the volume of foreign trade grew from about $38 billion in 1980 to about $290 billion in 1996: imports from about $20 billion to about $140 billion and exports from about $18 billion to about $151 billion. As a result, the share of imports and exports in the GDP increased distinctly, from a mere 5% each at the end of the 1970s to over 20% each in 1996. In this context, it is worth noting that in the second half of the 1990s nearly half of all foreign trade transactions were undertaken by enterprises which were either partially or completely in the possession of foreign investors. China's growing integration into the world market is expressed by the growing share of Chinese foreign trade in the global market. This share increased, for example, from 0.8% to 2% between 1978 and 1992. Statistical tests show that important domestic economic price ratios have since adjusted to global market price ratios. Nonetheless, the size of the country and the fact that the markets in some regions are not yet sufficiently developed still cause a plentitude of China-specific price ratios.</p>
            <p>China's willingness to accept foreign debt was initially expressed in negative foreign trade balances. Later, however, China exhibited not insignificant surpluses, which led to a quick increase in its foreign exchange reserves (<ref target="SIM-00274">balance of payments</ref>). It would be incorrect, however, to assume that this tendency of decreasing credit-financed imports indicates a reduction in the import of equipment and machines. Between 1993 and 1995 alone, China attracted nearly $100 billion worth of equipment, machines, and technology in the form of direct foreign investment.</p>
            <p>Changes in the commodity structure of China's foreign trade demonstrate its growing weight as a modern global economic partner. While the export-share of primary goods in 1980 was still 50% (of which foodstuffs alone accounted for 17% and petroleum and other products 24%), by 1995 it had fallen to 14%. The export-share of industrial products, by contrast, increased dramatically, from 50% in 1980 to 86% in 1995, which demonstrates China's growing competitiveness in high-order industrial products. Of significant importance here is the fact that among exported industrial goods the proportion of machines and means of transportation rose from 5% to 21%. Among imports the share of industrial good increased from 65% to 82% between 1980 and 1995; machines and equipment alone showed an increase from 26% to 40%. By contrast, the proportion of primary goods imported during the same period fell from 35% to 19%.</p>
            <p>The intention to regionally diversify foreign trade was extensively realized. China's most important foreign trade partners in 1997 were Japan, Hong Kong, the USA, and the EU. A regional breakdown of exports produces the following figures: Hong Kong 24%, Japan 17%, USA 18%, and EU 16%. In the same year, China obtained 20% of its imports from Japan, 11% from the USA, 18% from the EU, and 5% from Hong Kong. The development of bilateral trade between China and Taiwan is also noteworthy. In 1980 there had been effectively no trade relationship between the two. In 1997, by contrast, China exported 2% of its wares to Taiwan and Taiwanese good accounted for 11.5% of China's total imports (<ref target="COM-00008">foreign trade: Taiwan</ref>). In addition to the increasing regional diversification of Chinese foreign trade, the trend of growing integration of the Chinese economy into the Asian region deserves note. In 1980, China conducted 50% of its foreign trade with neighboring countries, particularly Japan and South Korea. By 1995 this figure had grown to 62%. The accumulation of intraregional trade can be seen as an indication that after the removal of barriers to foreign trade - initially imposed from outside and later self-imposed - the same basic structures began to reemerge which had historically characterized trade in the Asian region.</p>
            <p>At the beginning of the 21st century, many of the tendencies noted above continued. The foreign trade volume reached $510 billion in 2001 and climbed to $1422 trillion in 2005. In the same period, imports grew from $244 billion to $660 billion and exports from $266 billion to $762 billion. Owing to the export surplus and other speculative capital inflow, China's foreign currency reserves increased drastically and thus widened the scope of political action regarding its exchange rate policy. In 2005, the share of foreign trade in GDP reached more than 50%, highly unusual for an economy the size of China.</p>
            <p>Just like in the past decade, FDI constituted an important driving force of both foreign trade and economic growth. FDI grew from $47 billion in 2001 to $60 billion in 2005. A major part of Chinese exports is still owed to foreign direct investment in modern branches of production. This could be the reason why in 2005 the share of machines and transport equipment in exports climbed to 46%, while the share of products from the primary sector declined to mere 6%. Small changes are to be noted with regard to regional foreign trade, yet there are now fundamental differences from the situation that emerged in the mid-1990s. The same applies to China's economic integration in Asia.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_1_1"><title level="m">in the World Trading System. Defining the Principles of Engagement. The Hague et.al</title><editor><name>Abbott, Frederick MChina</name></editor><date>1998</date></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_2_1"><author><name>Cass, Deborah Z. and Williams, Brett and Barker, George Robert</name></author><title level="m">eds. China and the World Trading System: Entering the New Millennium</title><date>2005</date><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_3_1"><author><name>Chai, Joseph C.H.</name></author><title level="m">China: Transition to a Market</title><date>1997</date><pubPlace>Economy. Oxford</pubPlace></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_4_1"><author><name>Fairbank, John K.</name></author><title level="m">Trade and Diplomacy on the China Coast: The Opening of the Treaty Ports, 1842-1854</title><date>1953</date><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_5_1"><author><name>Klenner, Wolfgang and Wiesegart, Kurt</name></author><title level="m">Chinas Wirtschaftsstruktur und Reformen in Binnen- und Außenwirtschaft</title><date>1982</date><pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_6_1"><author><name>Klenner, Wolfgang</name></author><title level="m">Chinas Finanz- und Währungspolitik nach der Asienkrise. Bilanz und Perspektiven der Reformpolitik</title><date>2006</date><pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_7_1"><author><name>Lardy, Nicholas R.</name></author><title level="m">China in the World Economy</title><date>1994</date><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_8_1"><title level="m">The World Bank. "The Economy, Statistical System, and Basic Data." In China: Socialist Economic Development. 3 Volumes</title><date>1983</date><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_9_1"><author><name>Long-Term, Idem China</name></author><title level="m">Development Issues and Options.The Report of a Mission sent to China by the World Bank</title><date>1985</date><pubPlace>Baltimore/London</pubPlace></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00007_bibl_10_1"><author><name>Zeng, Ka</name></author><title level="m">China´s Foreign Trade Policy: The New Constituencies</title><date>2007</date><pubPlace>London</pubPlace></bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
