<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xs="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns:type="application/tei+xml" xml:id="COM-00016">
	  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Political Science</title>
            <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/search?query=local.names+all+%22Amaney A. Jamal%22">
               <name type="person">Amaney A. Jamal</name>
               <idno type="ORCID"/>
               <idno type="ISNI"/>
            </author>
            <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/search?query=local.names+all+%22Vickie Langohr%22">
               <name type="person">Vickie Langohr</name>
               <idno type="ORCID"/>
               <idno type="ISNI"/>
            </author>
            <funder ref="placeholder"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>BRILL</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Leiden | Boston</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="placeholder">Placeholder</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Women &amp; Islamic Cultures</title>
               <editor>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Suad</forename>
                     <surname>Joseph</surname>
                  </persName>
               </editor>
               <biblScope unit="volume"/>
               <biblScope unit="page">anniversary:269</biblScope>
               <idno type="DOI">10.1163/1872-5309_ewic_COM_00016</idno>
               <idno type="sams-id">ewic</idno>
               <idno type="publisher-id">EWIO</idno>
               <idno type="ISSN">1872-5309</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Middle East and Islamic Studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css" schemeVersion="3.0"/>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="italic">font:italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="bold">font:bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="underline">font:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="subscript">font:subscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="superscript">font:superscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallcaps">font:smallcaps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20140401" status="first-online"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
						      <head>Introduction</head>
						      <p>The literature on political science and women in the Muslim world (defined as countries in which Muslims are a majority or a plurality of the population) has centered on three main debates. The first examines the lack of democracies in the Muslim world compared to other regions (the “democracy deficit”) and asks whether gender discrimination has contributed to this deficit. The second set of debates asks why women in the Muslim world lag behind their counterparts in the rest of the developing world in areas such as representation in parliament and, particularly, in their participation in the workforce. The third focus of the literature looks to the ways women work within contexts often presumed to be patriarchal, such as Islamist political parties, to advance their own interests. This last strand contextualizes the sources of the barriers and opportunities that hinder or empower women. By and large, the political science literature on women in the Muslim world is a small field. This is perhaps driven more by the disciplinary boundaries of political science, where the study of women has not received adequate scholarly attention.</p>
						      <p>Because of this dearth of information and since several political science approaches such as political culture, identity, and political behavior strive to understand the micro-foundations of individual political behavior, the analysis in this entry extends beyond the formal field of political science and examines influential works on women and Islam from the fields of sociology and anthropology as well. The works from these other fields have also been influential in addressing questions of individual political agency and mobilization in the field of political science.</p>
					    </div>
         <div>
						      <head>Democracy and Women’s Rights</head>
						      <p>Scholarship in the first decade of the twenty-first century has argued that systematic discrimination against women is a key reason for the lack of democracy in the Muslim world. Steven Fish (2002) contends that women in countries in which Muslims are a plurality or a majority of the population <pb ana="A" n="270" corresp="1"/>suffer systematic discrimination and that this discrimination significantly hinders democratization. Fish assesses statistically quantifiable measures of women’s well-being such as the gap between male and female literacy rates, the gap in the numbers of men and women in parliament and in high-ranking executive branch positions, and the percentage of women and men in the population, known as the “sex ratio” (because when men significantly outnumber women in a country, this is often due to girls having less access to food and healthcare, or strong societal preferences for sons which lead to abortions of female fetuses or girl infanticide.) Fish compares these indicators in the 47 Muslim majority or plurality countries to countries across the globe. While holding economic development constant, Fish finds that Muslim countries perform worse on each of these indicators than non-Muslim countries. He then notes that performance on his gender indicators is correlated with Freedom House scores measuring countries’ levels of democracy.</p>
						      <p>Daniela Donno and Bruce Russett (2004) strongly challenge Fish’s findings, arguing that there is no connection between democracy and performance on gender indicators and that only Arab women, not Muslim women more generally, lag behind women in other regions. Donno and Russett used Fish’s indicators and added several additional measures of female empowerment, as well as using more precise measurements for indicators adopted by Fish. More importantly, they measured factors other than gender which could account for authoritarian rule in a particular country, such as the number of other democracies in the region (in accordance with well-substantiated findings that when some countries in a region democratize the chance of others doing so increases) and the number of fatal military disputes that a country participated in between 1991 and 2000 (to measure the extent to which war and militarization affect democratic and gender outcomes). In this fuller analysis, Donno and Russett found that all but one of these gender outcomes (women in government) were unrelated to democracy, concluding that “women’s rights exhibit virtually no independent influence on democracy” (2004, 593). They also found, counter to Fish, that Muslim countries do not perform particularly badly on gender outcomes, but Arab ones do, contending that “when Islam is in the equations without a separate variable for Arab, it often impacts negatively on women’s rights, but when a control for Arab states is in the equation it is that, not Islamic culture <hi rendition="#italic">per se</hi>, that regularly makes the difference” (599). In this analysis, then, Muslim countries are particularly likely to be authoritarian and Arab countries are particularly <pb ana="A" n="271" corresp="1"/>likely to oppress women, but levels of women’s rights explain the predominance of authoritarian government in the Arab or Muslim world.</p>
						      <p>In his 2011 book <hi rendition="#italic">Are Muslims Distinctive? A Look at the Evidence</hi>, Steven Fish argued that when he revisited his earlier hypothesis that gender inequality in Muslim countries was causally related to authoritarianism using different measurements and control factors, he no longer found a “stable relationship” between the two. Even after controlling for factors other than Islam which could affect democracy, such as length of national independence and population size, Fish continued to argue that there was a strong relationship between authoritarian rule and proportion of Muslims in the population (as opposed to the simple binary variable, in which countries were either Muslim—if a plurality of the population was Muslim—or not, employed in the 2002 article). He also found once again that “females tend to fare relatively poorly in places where Muslims predominate,” but that data that better measured the relevant variables suggested no clear link between gender inequality and authoritarian rule in the Muslim world (2011, 201).</p>
						      <p>Ronald Inglehart and Pippa Norris (2003a, 2003b) also contend that there is a causal link between women’s status in the Muslim world and authoritarian governance. In contrast to Fish, who measures women’s status with statistical measurements of socio-demographic indicators such as literacy gap and sex ratio, Inglehart and Norris cite opinion surveys to argue that attitudes towards women’s rights are significantly more patriarchal in the Muslim world than elsewhere. In <hi rendition="#italic">Rising Tide: Gender Equality and Cultural Change Around the World</hi>, they use answers to World Values Survey (WVS) questions asked in countries throughout the world to argue that Muslim societies have the world’s least supportive attitudes towards gender equality and that, more generally, “where there are more egalitarian attitudes, these are systematically related to the actual condition of men’s and women’s lives” (2003a, 10). In an article in <hi rendition="#italic">Foreign Policy</hi> (Inglehart and Norris 2003b), they explicitly connect the inegalitarian gender attitudes found in Muslim countries to the Muslim democracy deficit, arguing that “among all the countries included in the WVS, support for gender equality—a key indicator of tolerance and personal freedom—is closely linked with a society’s level of democracy” (2003b, 67). While surveys show that Muslims strongly support democracy as a political system, Inglehart and Norris contend that “democracy may not be sustainable in (Muslim) societies” due to their low levels of support for gender equality (65). In a 2007 working paper, “Democratic Deficit and Gender Attitudes. <pb ana="A" n="272" corresp="1"/>Do attitudes toward women affect women’s rights and level of democracy?”, Amaney Jamal and Vickie Langohr (2007) argue that inegalitarianism, as expressed in the more qualitative measure of gender attitudes revealed in WVS surveys, is not causally related to the democratic deficit in the Arab world. They find that although there is a link between inegalitarianism and objective indicators measuring women’s empowerment, these measures are not linked to levels of democracy.</p>
					    </div>
         <div>
						      <head>Modernization and Attitudes towards Gender</head>
						      <p>There is much agreement in the literature underscoring the primary factors that structure attitudes towards gender equality in the Muslim world. These can be organized under two main rubrics: cultural modernization and economic development. In a nutshell, societies that have undergone some level of socioeconomic modernization, particularly industrialization and urbanization, tend to have cultural attitudes that bode well for women’s equality. Similarly, accounts of the impact economic development has on women’s equality maintain that as women enter the labor force, a host of other factors, such as expanded rights and the ability to distance women from patriarchal dominance, ensue in ways that also support women’s equality.</p>
						      <p>In <hi rendition="#italic">Rising Tide</hi>, Inglehart and Norris concern themselves with the connection between economic development, culture, and gender attitudes. In what they call a “revised version of modernization theory,” they argue that as societies develop economically their attitudes towards the role of women change in predictable ways. Industrialization leads large numbers of women to become educated, work outside the home, have smaller families, and obtain the right to vote; in post-industrial societies women additionally gain more power in the workplace and in politics. These economic changes spark attitudinal shifts, as the importance of the traditional family declines, secularism spreads, and daily economic security allows citizens to turn from survival to self-expression values such as support for gender equality. In pre-industrial societies, by contrast, the constant struggle for economic survival and corresponding insecurity “develop(s) cultures mistrustful of rapid change, emphasizing the values of traditional authority and strong leadership . . . backed up by social sanctions and norms derived from religious authorities. In these societies, the traditional two-parent family, with its division of sex roles between male breadwinner and female caregivers, is crucial for . . . survival” (2003a, 16). <pb ana="A" n="273" corresp="1"/>Inglehart and Norris analyze 74 countries in which the WVS was conducted at least once between 1980 and 2000. Eleven of these were Muslim countries, including Bosnia-Herzegovina, Albania, Azerbaijan, Nigeria, and Bangladesh. Inglehart and Norris divide these countries on the basis of their Human Development Index (HDI) score into 21 postindustrial, 32 industrial, and 21 agrarian countries. They compare these countries’ attitudes on gender equality as measured by five WVS questions to levels of development indicated by logged per capita GDP and find that these countries cluster together predictably by group: with the exception of Japan, all of the postindustrial countries have high scores on the Gender Equality scale, the industrials have somewhat lower scores, and the agrarians have the lowest. Most Muslim countries fit into the agrarian cluster, with a few in the industrial cluster as well.</p>
						      <p>However, for Inglehart and Norris, economic change is not the only driver of attitudinal change: cultural and particularly religious traditions account for wide variations on support for gender equality even within groups of countries at the same level of economic and social development. They argue that of all the countries surveyed, “Muslims living in poorer, agrarian nations . . . are by far the most traditional group in their attitudes towards gender equality” (2003a, 68). Because this is true even once HDI scores, levels of democracy, and the social background of respondents (age, education, and so forth) are controlled for, the evidence indicates that traditional religious values and religious laws have played an important role in reinforcing inegalitarian social norms (68). In their <hi rendition="#italic">Foreign Policy</hi> article, Inglehart and Norris take this argument further to contend that the Muslim democracy deficit may well be caused by low support for gender equality in the Muslim world, since “among all countries in the WVS [World Values Survey], support for gender equality is closely linked with a society’s level of democracy” (2003b, 67). As a result, “Islamic religious heritage is one of the most powerful barriers to the rising tide of gender equality” (2003a, 49).</p>
						      <p>Inglehart and Norris express additional concerns pertaining to the status of women in the Muslim world. The poor attitudinal record of Muslims on gender quality exemplifies a more troubling pattern. Societies that have a more favorable opinion towards women also exemplify other important characteristics. They maintain that, “These issues are part of broader syndrome of tolerance, trust, political activism, and emphasis on individual autonomy that constitutes ‘self-expression values.’ ” Inglehart and Norris link these “self-expression values” to democratic institutions.</p>
						      <p>
               <pb ana="A" n="274" corresp="1"/>Mark Tessler and Eleanor Gao (2009) find that, ultimately, there are basic personality traits that unite people in their negative attitudes towards women. Parochial people, they maintain, are not tolerant of diverse political views, do not support gender equality, are not interested in politics, do not participate in civic and associational life, and are not trusting of fellow citizens. Conversely, citizens with a democratic orientation are more tolerant of diverse political views, support gender equality, are interested in political views, support gender equality, show interest in politics, participate in civic and associational life, and are trusting of fellow citizens.</p>
						      <p>A new wave of research has found significant variation in attitudinal orientations towards women. Helen Rizzo, Abdel-Hamid Abdel-Latif and Katherine Meyer (2010) find that non-Arab Muslim societies tend to exhibit higher levels of support for women’s rights than Arab Muslim societies. This is a finding echoed by Michele Angrist (2012). Rizzo et al. (2010) argue that one possible problem is that in the Arab world the link between anti-Americanism and anti-Westernism may explain negative attitudes towards gender equality, since gender equality norms are advanced by the West and in particular the United States. Hence, ideas about gender empowerment are linked to a hegemonic Western discourse, which is highly resisted in many sectors of Arab societies.</p>
						      <p>In addition to cultural arguments, there are several other explanations linked to the role of religion in hindering the advancement of women in the Muslim world. Religion as a category can be broken down into three main components: religion as denomination, individual-level religiosity, and the degree of secularism in a given state. The implication of these formulations is that religion in all its manifestations is bad for women. Thus, as modernization ensues, people should become less religious, societies should become more secular, and the denominational influences should dissipate. A plethora of studies substantiate these claims, including Inglehart and Norris’ <hi rendition="#italic">Rising Tide</hi>. Another strand of the modernization literature looks to the role of education and urbanization. As societies become more educated and more urban, their worldviews should become more cosmopolitan and universal. As such, their attitudes towards gender should improve, especially since higher levels of education and urbanization are seen as ways of shedding traditional norms and opinions in favor of more egalitarian concepts.</p>
						      <p>Economic modernization is deemed extremely useful for improving attitudinal predispositions towards women. This argument is best championed by Valentine Moghadam (2003). Economic development first allows women to enter the labor market, where they prove that they are <pb ana="A" n="275" corresp="1"/>capable of performing many of the same tasks as men, therefore signifying that they are equal to men in the workforce, and improve general attitudes about women’s competence and rights. Michael Ross (2008) also argues that labor market participation is important for advancing the status of women, but notes that increasing oil wealth often decreases women’s employment. In some countries, employed women tend to work almost exclusively in the production of tradable goods (such as clothing for export) but not in what Ross calls “nontraded” sectors, such as construction or sales, either because the physical labor requirements of these jobs exceed women’s capacity or because social norms discourage women from interacting with unrelated men. In these gender-segregated economies, oil booms decrease the number of women in the workforce by raising their reservation wage (the wage at which they will seek to enter the workforce), as the male-only nontradable sector of oil production provides higher wages to men in their families and government transfers increase family wealth. Because women do not join the labor force, they are more likely to have more children, less education, and less influence within families. Not working outside the home also renders women less likely to exchange information, to form networks to overcome collective action problems, and gain influence in the political sphere. It is important to note that for Ross, increases in oil production will not decrease women’s labor participation in countries which do not have gender-segregated economies, which is why, he argues, oil has not decreased women’s rights and influence in some Latin American countries such as Venezuela and Mexico, as well as in Muslim-majority Malaysia (110).</p>
						      <p>Aili Tripp, Alice Kang, Mounira Charrad, Pippa Norris and Teri Caraway all question Ross’s arguments in a 2009 issue of <hi rendition="#italic">Gender and Politics</hi>. For example, Pippa Norris (2009) suggests that one way to “disentangle the complex effects of Muslim religious faith and oil” would be to expand the logic of the argument—that employment in the oil sector is overwhelmingly male, and that this hurts women’s chances of winning elected office—to similarly male-dominated forms of natural resource extraction found in many regions of the world, such as the mining of gold and diamonds. Such an extension may not replicate Ross’s findings. As one example, Norris notes that South Africa’s economy was heavily dependent on mineral extraction but women there have very high levels of participation in political activism and in parliament.</p>
						      <p>In other political economy formulations that explain the status of women in Muslim societies, Lisa Blaydes and Drew Linzer (2008) argue that in societies where economic opportunities are few, women embrace <pb ana="A" n="276" corresp="1"/>“fundamentalist” practices, such as wearing the veil, to signal their marriage eligibility. The argument here is premised on the assumption (which is not substantiated in the article) that Arab men in general prefer marrying women who wear the veil. As such, women will opt to marry rather than risk competing in a labor force that offers few economic opportunities.</p>
						      <p>Many scholars discuss other macro-level factors that have influenced the status of Arab women in particular. Angrist (2012) argues that there are multiple explanations. Structural adjustment programs and austerity measures are seen as having a negative effect on women’s rights. Once states pulled back their social welfare programs, women across the Middle East disproportionately suffered because they were predominantly employed in the public sector (Doumato and Posusney 2003). Second, Arab states have been involved in more interstate wars than other states elsewhere. Warfare has had negative consequences on women, both in terms of economic opportunities and security vulnerabilities (Pratt and al-Ali 2009). Third, anti-Westernism has resulted in opposition to Western norms being imported into the Arab world. Increasing levels of Western intervention have made it more difficult for women to embrace women’s equality, as it is often seen as complicity with Western values and dictates. Furthermore, Arab societies have resisted the imposition of Western gender norms more vigorously than non-Arab Muslim states. Other scholars have found that high levels of anti-Westernism have served as a source of empowerment for Islamist movements, which often dictate the discourse on gender equality in ways unfavorable towards women ( Jamal and Langohr 2007, Langohr and Jamal 2012).</p>
						      <p>Sociologist Mounira Charrad (2001) wrote an influential analysis of the role of different paths of state formation in shaping different women’s personal status regimes in Maghrib states. The process through which tribes and clans were integrated into the nation state is crucial for understanding the variance in outcomes. Examining Morocco, Algeria and Tunisia from the pre-colonial period to the 1970s, Charrad finds that in states that had incorporated the tribes, customary laws also influenced the nature of personal status laws. This was more evident in Algeria and Morocco than in Tunisia. Jamal and Langohr (2012) further argue that, in fact, women tend to have more equitable personal status laws in countries where regimes have been willing to stand by a commitment towards women.</p>
						      <p>Laurie Brand (1998) wrote a very comprehensive book on women’s rights in the Arab world in the era of political liberalization. Her book examines the reasons why an expansion of women’s rights did not accommodate the expansion of political liberalization in many Arab states. Brand argues that the process of political liberalization itself is rather tumultuous <pb ana="A" n="277" corresp="1"/>and uncertain. These levels of uncertainty do not bode well for women. Exacerbating this tension is that external aid for women’s rights had been negatively tarnished as a “Western”-imposed agenda. In the process of asserting nationalist credentials, especially among groups that are otherwise liberal, women’s rights tended to be sacrificed. By contrast, linguistics scholar Ousseina Alidou (2008) notes that with the rise of democratization in Niger in the early 1990s came a significant increase of women doing activist work, including the creation of <hi rendition="#italic">makaranta</hi> or <hi rendition="#italic">madarasas</hi> to provide literacy for adult women—only 15 percent of whom were literate in 2005—through memorization of the Qurʾān. In the democratization period, the IMF and World Bank moved to privatize education in Niger, one of the poorest countries in the world, further limiting educational opportunities for poor boys and girls who were already largely excluded from a Francophone-dominant education system. Women activists responded to this with the creation of female-only Qurʾānic study sessions to provide literacy training for adult women. These sessions also provided space, and social sanction, for women to learn income-generating skills such as incense-making and hairdressing and encouraged “friendship gatherings” in which women provided economic support to friends.</p>
					    </div>
         <div>
						      <head>The Use of Existing Avenues</head>
						      <p>Although Muslim women, and Arab women in particular, enjoy less advantageous positions in cross-national perspectives, they have hardly been absent from key debates addressing social, economic and political realities. One increasingly fruitful field of research has been studies of the roles of women in Islamist political parties. While these male-dominated political parties espouse very conservative views of women’s roles, female party members have gained crucial organizational skills through their work in the parties, and in some cases have used their own knowledge of Islamic texts to discourage religiously-sanctioned practices such as polygamy, which they understand to be harmful to women.</p>
						      <p>In Yemen, Stacey Philbrick Yadav (2010) notes, the decline of the Yemeni Socialist Party and the rise of the Islamist Islah party as the most powerful opposition force in the country significantly increased gender segregation in the public sphere by the late 1990s. The Women’s Sector of the Islah party, however, provided an unparalleled opportunity for women to gain crucial skills, from raising funds to giving speeches to instructing other women in the Qurʾān.</p>
						      <p>
               <pb ana="A" n="278" corresp="1"/>Religious studies scholar Pieternella van Doorn-Harder’s study of women’s activities within the two biggest Islamic organizations in Indonesia, Nahdlatul Ulama and Muhammadiya, finds similar opportunities for women’s advancement, with one female leader telling a graduating high school class that through her own activism in Nasyiatul ʿAisyiyah, Muhammadiyah’s group for girls and young women, she “learned how to write proposals . . . sometimes phone a minister and . . . travel all over Indonesia,” and even traveled abroad (van Doorn-Harder 2006, 140). In contrast to many Muslim countries, Indonesia has a long tradition of girls having access to <hi rendition="#italic">pesantren</hi>, which van Doorn-Harder defines as “Islamic boarding schools” (van Doorn-Harder 2006, 2), producing a relatively large number of women deeply trained in Islamic texts. Nasyiatul ʿAisyiyah members have used this knowledge to offer more feminist readings of current Indonesian and Islamic norms. For example, Siti Ruhaini, one of three women added to the formerly male-only guidance bureau (Majlis Tarjih) of Muhammadiya in 1995, argues that “cooking, cleaning, and washing clothes are the man’s responsibility. Islam acknowledges that women’s tasks of giving birth and breastfeeding are heavy . . . giving birth and taking care of the baby are in principle tiring enough” (van Doorn-Harder 2006, 156).</p>
						      <p>Other scholars have looked at the ways in which participation in Islamic movements has helped women improve their overall status. Historian Margot Badran (2006) finds that women in Egypt have benefited from participation in Islamic movements, while political scientist Yeşim Arat (2005) sees the same phenomenon among women in Turkey’s Refah party.</p>
						      <p>Janine Clark and Jillian Schwedler examine the conditions under which women can rise to positions of authority in two Islamist parties, Islah in Yemen and the Islamic Action Front in Jordan. Writing in 2003, they explain how over the decade of the 1990s these two parties moved from strongly opposing women’s political participation to “not only hav[ing] women in their highest decision-making bodies but hav[ing] more [women] than any other party in either country” (Clark and Schwedler 2003, 293). Female party members exploited particular opportunities, such as disputes within the parties between moderates and hardliners. The rise of women to leadership positions, however, did not lead either party to consistently support increased public activism for female members, as was demonstrated when reformists in the IAF bowed to more hardline members and asked IAF women to leave public meetings in the summer of 1999 to discuss problems between the King and Hamas. Even while women face gendered barriers, they continue to push an inclusive agenda <pb ana="A" n="279" corresp="1"/>that works to their advantage. Historian Eleanor Doumato (2000) shows how some women (in Iran and Saudi Arabia, respectively) actively created a type of counter-orthodoxy and thus challenged the male-dominated orthodoxy by adopting marginal types of worship such as exclusively female performances, healing sessions, and saint worship. Sociologist Alessandra González (2012) finds that Kuwaiti women demanding political rights did so within the realm of traditional boundaries. They refused to see gender empowerment as undermining key traditional values, such as women’s importance in domestic affairs. In fact, these women wanted to maintain some of the comforts and values linked to patriarchal tradition. Although Kuwaiti women were influenced by the principles of equality, they wanted equality to coincide with a traditional value system.</p>
						      <p>A recent phenomenon in the literature on women and politics in the Middle East is the increasing number of women who incorporate Islam in their daily lives. Anthropological works, such as Saba Mahmood’s 2005 study of an Egyptian women’s mosque movement and Lara Deeb’s 2006 study of Lebanese Shiʿi communities have examined public piety. By adopting Islam, these women have turned what is usually considered an obstacle to women’s empowerment—their frequent exclusion from public spaces—into an opportunity to become active. Women tend to meet in homes and mosques where they dialogue, engage and question as in Yeşim Arat’s study (2005) of women in Turkey’s Refah Islamist party, mentioned earlier. Women in those parties developed their own understandings and interpretations of Islam that contrasted with secular voices. The women wanted headscarves but not polygamy, and they wanted an Islamic state because they associated it with a moral state.</p>
						      <p>Through a rich ethnography of poor Bangladeshi women, Elora Shehabuddin (2008a) finds that they carefully negotiate their support for political parties in the context of a failing state. She carefully shows that women’s support for Islamism should not simply be confined to a polarized secular-religious debate. Rather, there exist serious material grievances that structure the choices these women make. Shehabuddin (2008b) also extends this argument in her article “Jamaat-i-Islami in Bangladesh. Women, democracy and the transformation of Islamist politics.” Here, she argues that, over time, the Jamaat party, now engaged in the formal electoral process, has incorporated women in meaningful roles so as to privilege their individuality, as both mothers and voters in ways that can be empowering. This account of women’s participation in Islamist groups problematizes accounts that declare that women always participate in these movements from a position of subordination.</p>
						      <p>
               <pb ana="A" n="280" corresp="1"/>The one unifying feature of the works described here is the direct challenge to a Western hegemonic discourse of liberal feminism. These works advance the argument that there are different modalities for “feminist engagement.” Because women are using Islamic-authored channels, which at times serve as marginalized spheres of participation, women are nevertheless gaining a voice of empowerment and influence that they otherwise would not have obtained. These studies suggest that we cannot simply deem women’s behaviors as instances of political subordination or marginalization, when in fact the sources of women’s agency and empowerment are a complex and dynamic process.</p>
					    </div>
         <div>
						      <head>Conclusion</head>
						      <p>There remain multiple venues of research that are of vital importance. Little is known about women’s role in the formal political process. Do women comprise an electoral constituency? How might patriarchy influence the choice-set before them? Do formal political channels offer adequate opportunities for female representation? Farida Jalazai’s <hi rendition="#italic">Shattered, Cracked, or Firmly Intact?: Women and the Executive Glass Ceiling Worldwide</hi> (2013) is an excellent study of women and leadership in comparative perspective, which has received little attention.</p>
						      <p>In the field of political science, however, the study of gender remains on the fringes of the discipline. This is primarily because there is not a unified theory about the ways to operationalize gender, gender relations, gender identities, and gender politics in influential models of political science, especially those in cross-national or large N studies. The discipline is increasingly moving toward mixed method approaches, which means that there will remain several challenges to the study of gender and politics. Primarily, this will require the compilation, production, and coding of data made available in an accessible way. The turn to mixed methods however, will continue to underscore context-specific knowledge of the cases at hand. The study of Muslim women must also be committed to an understanding of the political contextual influences that continue to shape the constraints, opportunities and challenges they face. The qualitative-quantitative divide should not be constructed as an “either-or” paradigm, but rather one that speaks to a vigorous debate. Mixed method approaches will allow for a more nuanced understanding of the dynamics that shape women’s political lives, while paying attention to patterns that are generalizable across the Muslim world. Indeed, the route forward should build on the exemplary and influential works in this essay.</p>
					    </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_1_1d1e215">Al-Ali, Nadje and Nicola2009London Pratt (eds.). Women and war in the Middle East, .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_2_1d1e224">Alidou, Ousseina2008. Engaging modernity. Muslim women and the politics of agency in post-colonial Niger, Madison, Wisc. .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_3_1d1e233">Angrist, MicheleWar, resisting the West, and women’s labor. Toward an understanding of Arab12012), 51–82. exceptionalism, in Politics and Gender 8: (2012), 51–82.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_4_1d1e242">Arat, Yesim2005Albany, N.Y. Rethinking Islam and liberal democracy. Islamist women in Turkish politics, . .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_5_1d1e252">Badran, Margot2006Princeton, N.J. Feminists, Islam and nation. Gender and the making of modern Egypt, . .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_6_1d1e261">Blaydes, Lisa and A, DrewLinzer. The political economy of women’s support for fundamentalist Islam, inWorld Politics604 (2008), 576–609Blaydes, Lisa and Drew A. :4 (2008), 576–609.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_7_1d1e270">Brand, Laurie1998New York. Women, the state, and political liberalization, .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_8_1d1e279">Caraway, Teri L.42009), 568–575 Comparative political economy, gender and labor markets, in Politics and Gender 5: (2009), 568–575.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_9_1d1e288">Charrad, MouniraMorocco, Berkeley and Calif2001. States and women’s rights. The making of postcolonial Tunisia, Algeria and Morocco, Berkeley, Calif. .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_10_1d1e297">Charrad, MouniraKinship, Islam or oil. Culprits of gender42009), 546–53. inequality?, in Politics and Gender 5: (2009), 546–53.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_11_1d1e307">Clark, Janine and Schwedler, Jillian35: 3 (2003), 293–312Clark, Janine and Jillian Schwedler. Who opened the window? Women’s activism in Islamist parties, in Comparative Politics 35:3 (2003), 293–312.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_12_1d1e316">Deeb, Lara2006Princeton, N.J. An enchanted modern. Gender and public piety in Shiʾi Lebanon, . .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_13_1d1e325">Donno, Danielaand Bruce Russet. Islam, authoritarianism, and female empowerment. What are the linkages?, inWorld Politics 5642004), 582–607 : (2004), 582–607.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_14_1d1e334">Doorn-Harder, Pieternella vanIll2006. Women shaping Islam. Reading the Qur’an in Indonesia, Urbana, . .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_15_1d1e343">Doumato, Eleanor A.2000New York Getting God’s ear. Women, Islam, and healing in Saudi Arabia and the Gulf, .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_16_1d1e352">Doumato, Eleanor2003Boulder, Colo A.Getting God’s ear Women and Islam and Marsha P. Posusney (eds.), Women and globalization in the Arab Middle East. Gender, economy, and society, . .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_17_1d1e362">Fish, M.StevenIslam and authoritarianism, inWorld Politics5512002), 4–37Fish, M. Steven. : (2002), 4–37.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_18_1d1e371">Fish, MSteven2011New YorkFish, M.Steven. Are Muslims distinctive? A look at the evidence, .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_19_1d1e380">Gonzales, Allessandra2013New York. Islamic feminism in Kuwait. The politics and paradoxes, .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_20_1d1e389">Inglehart, Ronald and Norris, Pippa2003CambridgeInglehart, Ronald and Pippa Norris. Rising tide. Gender equality and cultural change around the world, a.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_21_1d1e398">Inglehart, Ronald and Norris, PippaThe true clash of civilizations, in ForeignPolicy1352003b), 62–70. (2003b), 62–70.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_22_1d1e407">Jamal, Amaney and Langohr, Vickie2007Jamal, Amaney and Vickie Langohr. Democratic deficit and gender attitudes. Do attitudes toward women affect women’s rights and level of democracy? Working paper, .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_23_1d1e414">Kang, AliceStudying oil, Islam and women as if institutions42009), 560–68. mattered, in Politics and Gender 5: (2009), 560–68.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_24_1d1e423">Langohr, Vickie and Jamal, AmaneyThe improvement of women’s rights in the Arab world. The importance of governing authorities2012New YorkLangohr, Vickie and Amaney Jamal. , in Governance in the Middle East and North Africa. A handbook, ed. Abbas Kandhim, , 133–54.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_25_1d1e432">Mahmood, Saba2005Princeton, N.J. Politics of piety. The Islamic revival and the feminist subject, . .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_26_1d1e441">Moghadam, Valentine M.2003Boulder, Colo Modernizing women. Gender and social change in the Middle East, 2nd edn., . .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_27_1d1e450">Norris, Pippa42009), 553–60. Petroleum patriarchy? A response to Ross, in Gender and Politics 5: (2009), 553–60.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_28_1d1e459">Rizzo, Helen and Abdel-Latif, Abdel-Hamid and Meyer, KatherineSociology 4162007), 1151–70Rizzo, Helen, Abdel-Hamid Abdel-Latif and Katherine Meyer. The relationship between gender equality and democracy. A comparison of Arab versus non-Arab Muslim societies, in : (2007), 1151–70.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_29_1d1e470">Ross, MichaelOil, Islam and women, inAmerican Political Science Review10212008), 107–23. : (2008), 107–23.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_30_1d1e479">Shehabuddin, Elora2008New York. Reshaping the holy. Democracy, development, and Muslim women in Bangladesh, a.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_31_1d1e488">Shehabuddin, EloraThe Jamaat-i Islami in Bangladesh. Women, democracy, and the transformation of Islamist politics, inModern Asian Studies422008b), 577–603. (2008b), 577–603.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_32_1d1e497">Tessler, Mark and Gao, EleanorGauging Arab support for democracy, inJournal of Democracy163 (2005), 83–97Tessler, Mark and Eleanor Gao. :3 (2005), 83–97.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_33_1d1e506">Tripp, AiliDebate. Does oil wealth hurt women?42009) 545–82. , in Politics and Gender 5: (2009) 545–82.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00016_bibl_34_1d1e515">Yadav, StaceySegmented publics and Islamist women in Yemen. Rethinking space and activism, inJournal of Middle East Women’s Studies62010["20", "1–30."]. :20 (), 1–30.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
