<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xs="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns:type="application/tei+xml" xml:id="EWICCOM-0090c">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Household Forms and Composition: Iran and Afghanistan</title>
            <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/search?query=local.names+all+%22Erika Loeffler Friedl%22">
               <name type="person">Erika Loeffler Friedl</name>
               <idno type="ORCID"/>
               <idno type="ISNI"/>
            </author>
            <funder ref="placeholder"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>BRILL</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Leiden | Boston</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="placeholder">Placeholder</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Women &amp; Islamic Cultures</title>
               <editor>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Suad</forename>
                     <surname>Joseph</surname>
                  </persName>
               </editor>
               <biblScope unit="volume"/>
               <biblScope unit="page">250</biblScope>
               <idno type="DOI">10.1163/1872-5309_ewic_EWICCOM_0090c</idno>
               <idno type="sams-id">ewic</idno>
               <idno type="publisher-id">EWIO</idno>
               <idno type="ISSN">1872-5309</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Middle East and Islamic Studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css" schemeVersion="3.0"/>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="italic">font:italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="bold">font:bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="underline">font:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="subscript">font:subscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="superscript">font:superscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallcaps">font:smallcaps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20090101" status="first-online"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Households vary with class and location. Traditional
agricultural/pastoral
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
contain an extended patrilineal/patrilocal family spanning several
generations, forming a production and consumption unit with
complementary sexual division of labor. In urban and non-agricultural
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
women do not produce much (except children); they prepare food and
provide care with materials provided by the men. These
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
change to nuclear family patterns earlier than agricultural ones under
the influence of changing work patterns, limited urban spaces, and
modernist ideas. Traditional wealthy urban
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
usually are the largest, including multiple wives of the household head,
an extended family, other relatives, and servants.</p>
         <p>Structurally, the developmental logic of the extended family informs
household composition and relationships: a man will try to exert control
over wife (wives) and sons as early and as long as possible, staying in
his father's house, compound, or camp and identifying with
his father's and brothers' interests as long as
necessary or advantageous for him. Eventually, he will establish an
independent nuclear household, which leads to the next
ex<anchor xml:id="P-V2P253"/>
                  <!-- <page id="P-V2P253" v="2" p="253" c="1"></page> -->tended family
as his sons bring their wives into the household. The sons, in turn,
will start the circle anew. Households of extended families are
structurally unstable.</p>
         <p>Practically, this household form ranges from a production and consumption
unit under one roof (including several wives) to a loosely cooperating
production unit with different contributions (cash from a teacher son,
labor from a farmer son) and separate consumption, as different nuclear
families (or mother and children units in polygynous families) live in
separate rooms in a compound, apartments in a house, or tents in a camp.
Built into these structures are the demand for cooperation, resentment
of authoritarian relations, and competition for resources especially
among married brothers. It is said that nothing breaks up a household
faster than brothers' wives fighting with each other and with
their mother-in-law. Co-wives are proverbially adversary. This is mostly
due to the household structure: co-wives are pitched against each other
as are sons' wives, and all against their mother-in-law over
resources and workloads; mothers-in-law back their sons, especially in
polygynous marriages, because sons are their source of power and of
support in old age. The often bad relationship between mother-in-law and
daughter-in-law leads to many old women's reliance on their
own visiting daughters for care.</p>
         <p>Rich men are more likely to be polygynous than are poor men (although any
man may be saddled with his dead brother's widow in addition
to his own wife), but they can also maintain separate homes for their
wives, minimizing contact and potential strife among them. Such
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
in effect are headed by a woman, with a visiting husband. There are
reports of older wives selecting a young wife for their husband for
various reasons. The first wife will usually stay in charge of the
household, including management of co-wives and supervising work. In the
wealthy
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
of the past, male and female servants did most of the menial chores;
with the trend toward nuclear families such large
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
have become rare. Modernity is expected to lower the rate of polygyny,
but especially in
<!--<index index="Names" display="Iran" level1="Iran">-->Iran<!--</index>-->
today many wealthy professional men are said to maintain several wives.
Women in
<!--<index index="Names" display="Iran" level1="Iran">-->Iran<!--</index>-->
today are admonished to stipulate a separate home if they contract a
marriage with a married man.</p>
         <p>While sons may stay in their father's household with their
wives, daughters leave upon marriage and are replaced by their
brother's wives. As strangers to the husband's
people and to each other, ignorant of the new household's
customs, the
<anchor xml:id="P-V2P253A"/>
                  <!-- <page id="P-V2P253A" v="2" p="253" c="2"></page> -->young wives
must expect to be everybody's servants. Unless the
mother-in-law is amiable and the young woman is hard-working and
cooperative, tensions and emotional and physical abuse are frequent.
Expected to keep wives and children under control and to side with
father, brothers, mother (in this order), a man will not likely support
his wives against his own people. Contrary to Islamic law, daughters
especially in lower classes and rural areas do not inherit, making them
the more vulnerable economically. In instances of hostile relations,
only through separation from the extended household can a woman gain
peace and control over resources in the house, including, eventually,
over her own daughters-in-law. An old or widowed woman expects to live
in the nuclear-to-extended household of a son (the youngest, where
ultimogeniture is practiced). Only if earlier she had established warm
relationships with the daughter-in-law who now is responsible for her
care can she hope realistically to be treated well. Recently, there is a
notable increase in the number of old women (but not old men) living
alone by choice, especially in
<!--<index index="Names" display="Iran" level1="Iran">-->Iran<!--</index>-->,
with financial assistance of their sons. An old widower will stay with a
son if he does not take another wife and establish a new nuclear
household. Since about 1990, as marriage age and divorce rates are
increasing (in
<!--<index index="Names" display="Iran" level1="Iran">-->Iran<!--</index>-->),
single-person
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
have increased in cities as have
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
of several unmarried young women (or men) renting an apartment to share
costs, and even women-headed
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
with children. Any household, especially in cities, at times will
include temporary residents such as a wife's parents, a
relative who is indigent, in need of education or medical care, or who
can provide childcare.</p>
         <p>Men have few household duties and skills and rely on service from women.
In the traditional
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
with many children and complementary gender roles, the division of labor
made sense to people. In the new, nuclear middle-class
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
with fewer children (in
<!--<index index="Names" display="Iran" level1="Iran">-->Iran<!--</index>-->),
women accuse men of being lazy and indolent, especially if the women
work outside the home. New patterns for household forms and
relationships are developing especially in socially dynamic
<!--<index index="Names" display="Iran" level1="Iran">-->Iran<!--</index>-->,
where people aspire to middle-class lifestyles, while war and the social
ideology of the
<!--<index index="Names" display="Taliban" level1="Taliban">-->Taliban<!--</index>-->
in
<!--<index index="Names" display="Afghanistan" level1="Afghanistan">-->Afghanistan<!--</index>-->
have encouraged large, traditionally structured
<!--<index index="SubIndex" display="households" level1="households">-->households<!--</index>-->
including many children, the extended family and/or multiple wives and
other relatives.</p>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EWICCOM-0090c_bibl_1_1d1e142"><author><name>M.</name></author><title level="m"/><editor><name>Austin, Tex</name></editor><date>2002</date><pubPlace>157–62</pubPlace><unclear> Afkhami, Death of the patriarch, in E. W. Fernea (ed.), Remembering childhood in the Middle East, . , .</unclear></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="P-V2P254"><author><name>Doubleday, V.</name></author><title level="m">Three women of Herat</title><date>1988</date><unclear>V. Doubleday, , Austin, Tex. .</unclear></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EWICCOM-0090c_bibl_3_1d1e177"><author><name>S.</name></author><title level="m">Farman-Farmaian, Daughter of Persia</title><date>1992</date><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EWICCOM-0090c_bibl_4_1d1e186"><author><name>Friedl, E.</name></author><title level="m"/><date>1989</date><pubPlace>Washington, D.C</pubPlace><unclear>E. Friedl, Women of Deh Koh. Lives in an Iranian village, . .</unclear></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EWICCOM-0090c_bibl_5_1d1e195"><author><name>Guppy, S.</name></author><title level="m">The blindfold horse. Memories of a Persian childhood</title><date>1988</date><pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace><unclear>S. Guppy, ,  .</unclear></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EWICCOM-0090c_bibl_6_1d1e205"><author><name>Hansen, H.</name></author><title level="m"/><date>1961</date><pubPlace>Copenhagen</pubPlace><unclear>H. Hansen, The Kurdish woman's life,  .</unclear></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EWICCOM-0090c_bibl_7_1d1e214"><author><name>Kousha, M.</name></author><title level="m">Voices from Iran. The changing lives of Iranian women</title><date>2002</date><pubPlace>Syracuse, N.Y</pubPlace><unclear>M. Kousha, , . .</unclear></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EWICCOM-0090c_bibl_8_1d1e227"><author><name>Tapper, N.</name></author><title level="m"/><date>1991</date><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><unclear>N. Tapper, Bartered brides. Politics, gender, and marriage in an Afghan tribal society,  .</unclear></bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
