<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:rng="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
     xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
     xmlns:xs="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
     xmlns:type="application/tei+xml"
     xml:id="COM-129">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Archaeological Textiles</title>
            <title level="a" type="sub">Archaeological Textiles</title>
            <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/search?query=local.names+all+%22Penelope Walton Rogers%22">
               <name type="person">Penelope Walton Rogers</name>
               <idno type="ORCID"/>
               <idno type="ISNI"/>
            </author>
            <funder ref="placeholder"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>BRILL</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Leiden | Boston</pubPlace>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Medieval Dress and Textiles</title>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume"/>
               <biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
               <idno type="DOI">10.1163/2213-2139_emdt_COM_129</idno>
               <idno type="sams-id">emdt</idno>
               <idno type="publisher-id"/>
               <idno type="ISBN">9789004124356</idno>
               <idno type="ISSN">2213-2139</idno>
               <idno type="URI">http://referenceworks.brillonline.com/entries/encyclopedia-of-medieval-dress-and-textiles/*COM_129</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p><!-- <info><sumpara>Textiles and other fibre products from archaeological excavations: survival, analysis, significance and a review of evidence from the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> centuries.</sumpara></info> --></p>
         </abstract>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>History</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css" schemeVersion="3.0"/>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="italic">font:italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="bold">font:bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="underline">font:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="subscript">font:subscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="superscript">font:superscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallcaps">font:smallcaps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20120503" status="first-print">Print publication</change>
         <change when="20120423" status="first-online"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>The term 'archaeological textile' embraces a wide range of fibrous products recovered from the earth or from submerged sites such as shipwrecks. Although 'textile' in its strictest sense means 'something woven', its meaning is usually extended to include non-woven goods such as felt, knitting and netting. These represent some of the most difficult artefacts to be managed in the post-excavation process: their fragility means that they need careful handling and their complexity makes them costly to record. On the other hand, they provide some of the most valuable insights into the medieval world.</p>
         <p>A distinction has to be drawn between excavated evidence and 'historical textiles', the term applied to garments and cloths which have survived above-ground, in treasuries or private hands. Historical textiles may be contemporary with archaeological material, but they tend to be individual whole items, often made from valuable materials, such as <ref target="SIM-001097">silk</ref> and gold, and they have usually been preserved because of an association with a particular person, office or religious belief. Archaeological textiles are nearly always fragmentary, heavily stained from burial and include a much wider range of fabric-type, from sacking (see <ref target="SIM-000879">sacks</ref>) to silk. They often occur in large numbers and where there is good stratigraphy they can be arranged in a dated sequence. By relating the textiles to sequences of textile tools, the textile industry and its development over time can be reconstructed. Just as importantly, by comparing the textile types from different categories of site -- urban, rural, ecclesiastical, royal, domestic, workshop or quayside -- social issues and status can be addressed.</p>
         <p>
						      <hi rendition="#bold">Textile survival and its effect on the evidence</hi>
					    </p>
         <p>Textiles can enter the ground in a formal way, as clothing or shrouds for the inhumed body, or they can be discarded in middens and pits, or lost at the edges of rooms and walkways. Once buried, their survival depends on the material from which they were made and how that interacts with the burial environment. In practice, textiles are most commonly found in two circumstances, in graves and on waterlogged sites.</p>
         <p>Graves are rarely dug into waterlogged ground and when a clothed body is placed in an earth-fast grave, in open ground, it is immediately exposed to alternating wet and dry conditions and fluctuating temperatures. This is extremely harmful to organic materials and most textiles will deteriorate or disappear within a decade or so of burial. In early Anglo-Saxon cemeteries, however, the body was often buried with metal artefacts, and small areas of textile can survive on the metalwork, sometimes because corrosion products act as a biocide, and sometimes because the minerals replace or form a cast of the textile fibres. The generic term for textiles preserved in association with metalwork is 'mineral-preserved'; the casts or replacements are called 'mineralised'.</p>
         <p>The Anglo-Saxon clothed burial ritual had mostly come to an end by the beginning of the 8<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century, although the Norse briefly re-introduced the practice into northern Britain and Ireland. As clothed burial gave way to linen shrouding, textiles ceased to be preserved except in rare circumstances. At St Bee's Priory, Cumbria, for example, the body had been sealed in lead and when opened there proved to be two, almost-intact, linen shrouds. Burials inside churches are less exposed to the elements and late examples of clothed burial are sometimes encountered. Mass vestments can be found in priests' coffins, hair cloth (see <ref target="COM-353">cilicium: hair cloth</ref>) in monks' graves and remains of <ref target="SIM-000941">wool</ref> clothing on the bodies of lay people granted 'intra-mural' burial.</p>
         <p>Textiles are preserved in waterlogged sites because the water excludes air, and with it harmful fungi and aerobic bacteria. The peat bogs of Ireland and Scotland represent a suitable environment for the preservation of wool clothing (their acidic nature being hostile to <ref target="COM-423">linens</ref>), but apart from the <ref target="COM-487">Orkney Hood</ref> (dated between the 3<hi rendition="#superscript">rd</hi> and early 7<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century), no significant medieval finds have as yet been made. In the wet conditions of early medieval crannogs (see <ref target="COM-249">crannog</ref>) (man-made islands), textiles have sometimes survived, as, for example, at Lagore in Meath, Ireland, and Llan-Gors (see <ref target="COM-372">Llan-Gors decorated garment</ref>) near Brecon in Wales.</p>
         <p>More commonly, waterlogged textiles are recovered from urban excavations. In low-lying areas of towns such as Aberdeen, Perth, Newcastle upon Tyne, York (see <ref target="COM-699">York: textile production</ref>) London (see <ref target="SIM-000942">London: archaeology</ref>), <ref target="COM-276">Dublin</ref>, <ref target="COM-673">Waterford</ref> and Cork, pits and ditches drop down below the water table, and there is a substantial build-up of water-retaining organic matter, representing centuries of dumped refuse. From this mildly acidic environment, wool and silk textiles can emerge in large quantities and in good condition, although heavily stained. Linens, on the other hand, are rarely encountered, except in towns such as Norwich and Canterbury, where the organic deposits are neutralised by chips of chalk brought up from the underlying bedrock. If linens are charred before burial, this too will improve their chances of survival, probably because the cellulosic component attractive to micro-organisms has been lost. For the most part, however, wool dominates textile collections from urban excavations. Since the revival of towns did not begin until the mid-9<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century, large groups of well-preserved textiles do not occur before this time.</p>
         <p>
						      <hi rendition="#bold">Analysis and research</hi>
					    </p>
         <p>Accurate analysis is essential to the study of archaeological textiles. A low-power microscope is used to record weave, spin, thread-count (per cm), yarn type, soft-finishing, seams, hems and wear patterns. For the identification of fibres, a high-power (x400-x600) optical microscope is necessary; scanning-electron microscopy is useful for mineralised fibres and a polarised light microscope helps distinguish between the different plant fibres. Where wool has been identified, its quality can be categorised by measuring the diameters of 100 fibres; and natural pigmentation can be determined by the size and density of pigment granules. Dyes are not always visible, or indeed preserved, but they can be investigated by extracting any colorant present into solvents and examining the extracts by absorption spectrophotometry and chromatography. The analysis of stable isotopes can help identify the geographic origin of the wool in broad terms.</p>
         <p>The technical details of the textiles are then compared with established databases and correlated with raw materials and tools from the site, in order to establish which material is local and which imported. Historical evidence is brought to bear and other excavated material considered. The aim is to build up a picture of the use of textiles at the site through different periods, and to address the significance of the finds in a local and national context.</p>
         <p>In many ways, medieval textiles reflect changes within society. Their evolution over the period in question runs parallel to the social and economic development of the country.</p>
         <p>
						      <hi rendition="#bold">The 5<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> to 9<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> centuries</hi>
					    </p>
         <p>The end of the Roman period saw the collapse of towns and commercial networks, followed by the rise of small, self-sufficient agricultural settlements. These settlements were mainly built on light, free-draining land, where textiles are not preserved, although surviving textile equipment demonstrates that cloth was being made there. The products of the settlement weavers are represented by the mineral-preserved textiles in the cemeteries.</p>
         <p>The garment accessories and costume styles found in the cemeteries are essentially Germanic in origin, but many of the people buried there are likely to have been acculturated British, and there is some evidence for the survival of Romano-British textile techniques such as 2 x 1 twill, tubular selvedges and soft-finishing (a teaselled and sheared nap). Most 5<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi>-century burials, however, are dominated by 2 x 2 twill with ZZ <ref target="COM-598">spinning</ref>, the standard fabric-type of the North European lowlands and south Scandinavia. It was mostly plain twill, but there were some examples of 2 x 2 diamond twill. Much of this material is wool, but linen tabby and linen 2 x 2 twill is also present. ZS wool twills, which had existed in the Roman period, re-appeared around A.D. 500, at about the same time as the hemispherical spindle whorl, and both are likely to represent a re-introduction from the Continent. Diamond and chevron twills formed a significant part of the ZS twill category. Linen ZZ tabby appears more frequently in 7<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi>-century graves although this probably reflects a change in burial practice, rather than an increase in availability. Throughout the Anglo-Saxon period, colour-patterning in the form of stripes and checks was rare and mostly confined to blanket-quality fabrics. In the early period, natural wool colours were used, but white cloths were sometimes dyed (see dyeing; <ref target="SIM-001003">colour and weave effectts</ref>) blue, green, brown or yellow, with woad, weld or greenweed and tannin-based dyes. Reds and purples from bedstraw and lichen were limited to small items and trimmings.</p>
         <p>Tablet-weaving (see <ref target="COM-619">tablet weave</ref>) had existed in Britain before the Anglo-Saxons, but the period saw a sudden proliferation of new types and most of the techniques seen in late medieval work can be traced back to 5<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi>- or 6<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi>-century introductions. Simple corded and textured effects worked on two-hole or four-hole tablets were commonly used for cuffs, garment borders and attachment braids (though probably not girdles). There were regional specialities, such as twill-based weaves and weft-wrapping techniques in northern England and East Anglia, and double-faced repp-effect bands in Kent. Gold-brocading appeared in women's burials in Kent in the 6<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century, the gold thread (see <ref target="COM-344">gold and silver metal thread</ref>) being flat strip at this time. The ground weave has disappeared from these bands, but the tie-down points are preserved as indentations in the gold strip.</p>
         <p>Although most textiles would be produced in the settlements, a small number of imports are identifiable. The coverlet weave 'summer-and-winter' was probably brought to Britain by merchants from the Mediterranean world. The small pattern repeat known as rosette weave was almost certainly made in the Frankish-controlled Rhineland and introduced into England via Kent; and spin-patterned linen tabby may have arrived by the same route. Those ZS diamond twills which have a regular pattern repeat of 20/Z x 18/S threads per diamond are possibly Frisian imports. The origin of pile weaves, used for rugs and cloaks, is unclear, but at a later date they were made in the Nordic countries and Ireland.</p>
         <p>The weave structures of the late 6<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> and 7<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century remained much as before, but there was a shift in their distribution. Society was changing at this time, leaders were emerging who were founding royal dynasties and, as a more hierarchical social structure evolved, valuable textiles transferred into male, especially high-status male, burials. <ref target="COM-288">Embroidery</ref> and patterned tablet weaves are still found in the graves of women, but gold thread and imported fabrics were now almost exclusively a male preserve. In the chamber of the <ref target="COM-568">Ship Burial</ref> at Sutton Hoo, Suffolk, there were fine wool textiles, madder-dyed cloths, coverlets and hangings and a piled-weave cloak, while there were garments with gold-brocaded borders in the princely burials at Prittlewell and Taplow.</p>
         <p>There are few contemporary textiles from Ireland, Scotland or Wales, although there is evidence for the export of madder from France to Ireland and it is likely that the Irish Sea region maintained links with the post-Roman Mediterranean world. In the western cemeteries of Anglo-Saxon England, where a native British or 'Welsh' element might be expected, plain 2 x 2 ZZ twill and ZZ tabby (in wool and linen) dominate and tablet weaves are few: this bears comparison with the textiles from Lagore Crannog, Ireland. In England there is a lacuna in the evidence for the 8<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> and early 9<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> centuries, but since the textiles from the later 9<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi>-century urban sites are much like those of the 7<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi>-century cemeteries, it seems reasonable to suppose that there was continuity in between.</p>
         <p>
						      <hi rendition="#bold">Transition in the 9<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> and 10<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> centuries</hi>
					    </p>
         <p>The 9<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century saw towns such as York (see <ref target="COM-699">York: textile production</ref>) London and Winchester emerging as centres for trade, administration and craft production. At the same time, Scandinavians arrived in the British Isles, first as raiders, then as traders and settlers. Norse burials in the Northern Isles, the Isle of Man, mainland Scotland, Ireland and northern England have yielded mineral-preserved textiles much like those in Scandinavia. They are predominantly ZZ tabby (probably all linen), some spin-patterned and some repps; piled weaves; and plain and diamond-patterned wool 2 x 2 ZZ twills. A brocaded weave with parallels only in Sweden and Denmark was found on a casket in a grave at Scar, Orkney.</p>
         <p>In <ref target="COM-276">Dublin</ref>, the Vikings founded a settlement, and rich organic deposits have yielded some 2,000 fragments of wool and silk textiles. These include the same textile types as in the graves just described, with the addition of the plain, diamond and chevron ZS twills which are commonly found in other towns of the period. There are also silk and wool tablet-woven bands, and an example of the Scandinavian technique, <ref target="COM-465">
							nålebinding
						</ref>. The number of silks at Dublin must owe much to the long-distance trade links established by Scandinavian merchants.</p>
         <p>Silk ribbons and headdresses appeared in England at the same time, especially in towns within the Scandinavian-controlled Danelaw. In York, there is evidence for a Scandinavian presence in a sock made by <hi rendition="#italic">nålebinding</hi>, a fragment of <ref target="COM-671">wadmal</ref> (a 2 x 2 twill with dark warp, pale weft, and a matted appearance), and a textile with a raised shaggy nap. These are comparatively rare, however, and most of the textiles and textile tools in York appear to be typically Anglo-Saxon. Madder red was by now the chief dye in York and London, in contrast with lichen purple in Viking Dublin and Early Norse sites of the North Atlantic, and woad blue in burials in Norway. Evidently, some regional traditions were being maintained.</p>
         <p>During the 9<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century, wool and linen cloth production in Anglo-Saxon towns differed little from the rural industry. Textiles were still spun, woven and dyed on one set of premises and the fabric types remained much the same as before. During the course of the 10<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century, however, changes occurred that heralded the beginning of the transition to late medieval guild (see <ref target="COM-350">guilds: London</ref>) production. The old 2 x 2 twills were slowly displaced by 2 x 1 twills, which included fine 2 x 1 diamond twill, made in glossy combed-wool yarns. At the same time, the evidence for the warp-weighted loom (see <ref target="SIM-000829">looms</ref>) disappeared in towns, though it lingered in the countryside, and it has been suggested that the new 2 x 1 twill structures were woven on the two-beam vertical loom. In York, raw materials were being brought in from outside and some dye materials were imported from abroad. It seems likely that town and country were now producing different fabric types and that towns were starting to view some of their products as a commercial commodity.</p>
         <p>
						      <hi rendition="#bold">The 11<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> to 15<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> centuries</hi>
					    </p>
         <p>Textiles of the late medieval period divide into two major date groups, the changeover period being the 14<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century. Collections of the 11<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> to mid-14<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century are dominated by wool 2 x 1 twill, including fine 2 x 1 diamond twill. The earliest of the plain 2 x 1 twill group often have irregularities in the weaving, visible knots and overlaps in the weft, and yarns which are under- or over-spun, all of which suggests an unstable phase in the industry. Chevron and diamond 2 x 2 twill and most plain 2 x 2 twills had disappeared with the warp-weighted loom, although some plain twills in fine qualities remained.</p>
         <p>During the course of the 14<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century there was a major shift, from 2 x 1 twill back to tabby and 2 x 2 twill. Soft-finishing was applied more frequently than before and in some cases taken to a very high standard: by the 15<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century, fine, softly draping napped fabrics comparable with those seen in Renaissance paintings appear in the archaeological record and textiles are more readily characterised by their thread-count and degree of fulling (see <ref target="COM-328">fulling and fulling mills in the British Isles</ref>) or teaselling-and-shearing, rather than their weave. 2 x 1 diamond twill disappeared, but 2 x 2 twill made from combed-wool yarns was joined in the 15<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century by lighter, finer fabrics, precursors of a more common textile type of the 16<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century. Linens are rare in the late medieval archaeological record but, where they occur, they are woven in plain tabby-weave in a range of qualities.</p>
         <p>The phases of technical change coincide with the horizons recognised by documentary historians. The 12<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century saw separate guilds of weavers and dyers appearing in towns, and wool textiles were now woven in the workshops of predominantly male artisans, who were using both the two-beam vertical loom and the new horizontal treadle-operated loom. Women, who had previously been in control of the whole process, were now mostly relegated to the supply of yarn. The start of this phase coincides with the period when standards of production visibly collapse.</p>
         <p>The changeover in archaeological textile types in the 14<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century corresponds with the arrival of new technology in the later 13<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> and 14<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> centuries. New tools included the long-toothed <ref target="COM-692">wool comb</ref>, hand cards and the spindle wheel (an early form of spinning wheel (see <ref target="COM-599">spinning wheels</ref>)), and the written sources show the industry dividing into two wings, one producing combed-wool worsteds (see <ref target="COM-697">worsted</ref>) and the other carded <ref target="SIM-000975">woollens</ref>. At the same time, there was a shift in the focus of production from the town to the countryside. Much cloth production was by this time geared towards sale, and the names of traded cloths often acquired the name of a small country town. Cloth was now sealed, to indicate that it had paid tax, using the lead seals (see <ref target="COM-555">seals (for cloth) and merchants' marks</ref>) sometimes found on excavations.</p>
         <p>Although it is impossible to recognise most named fabrics in the archaeological record, certain distinctive types have been tentatively identified. <ref target="COM-352">'Haberget'</ref>, a cloth named in Magna Carta, has been equated with 2 x 1 diamond twill. <ref target="COM-527">'Ray'</ref>, imported from Flanders, is likely to have been the tabby-weave wool cloth with coloured bands of extended tabby found in 13<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi>- and 14<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi>-century sites. 'Linsey-woolsey' is a textile with a linen warp and wool weft, which emerges from the ground as panels of weft yarn from which the warp has decayed. Sackcloth made from animal hair has been identified with the material known as 'cilicium' (see <ref target="COM-353">cilicium: hair cloth</ref>).</p>
         <p>Tablet-weaving, often in highly complex weaves, continued in use, for girdles, hair-bands and garment trims. Silk hairnets and finger loop braids (see <ref target="COM-311">finger loop braiding</ref>) also occur. <ref target="SIM-000900">Felt</ref> is a comparatively rare find, but there are small off-cut pieces, probably from hats (see <ref target="COM-360">hat</ref>), dated to the 14<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> and 15<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> centuries and knitted goods also appear. The date that the craft of knitting arrived is not clear -- it may have been as early as the 14<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century – but most evidence comes from the second half of the 15<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century. At any rate, by the end of the 15<hi rendition="#superscript">th</hi> century, all the major techniques and textile types of the post-medieval period had been established.</p>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_1_1">Crawford, B. E. and Ballin Smith, B., The Biggings, Papa Stour, Shetland: the History and Archaeology of a Royal Norwegian Farm, Society of Antiquaries of Scotland Monograph Series No. 15 (Edinburgh: 1999).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_2_1">Crowfoot, E., Pritchard, F. and Staniland, K.,Textiles and Clothing c.1150-c.1450, Medieval Finds from Excavations in London 4 (London: 1992).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_3_1">Granger-Taylor, H. and Pritchard, F., 'A fine quality Insular embroidery from Llan-gors Crannog, near Brecon' in Ed. M. Redknap, N. Edwards, S. Youngs, A. Lane and J. Knight, Pattern and Purpose in Insular Art, Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on Insular Art held at the National Museum and Gallery, Cardiff 3-6 September 1998 (Oxford: 2001), 91-9 and plates IV-VI.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_4_1">Gabra-Sanders, T., 'Textiles, textile fibres and animal hairs, dyes and ropes' in A. S. Cameron and J. A. Stones, Aberdeen: an In-depth View of the City's Past, Society of Antiquaries of Scotland Monograph Series No.19 (2002), 222-41.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_5_1">Heckett, E ., "The Textiles" in M. F. Hurley, 'Excavations of part of the medieval city wall at Grand Parade, Cork', Journal of the Cork Historical and Archaeological Society 249 (1985), 65-90 at 85-7.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_6_1">Heckett, E. W., 'Textiles, cordage, basketry and raw fibre' in Ed. M. Hurley, O. Scully, and S. McCutcheon, Late Viking Age and Medieval Waterford Excavations 1986-92 (Waterford: 1997).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_7_1">Henry, P., 'Changing weaving styles and fabric types: the Scandinavian influence' in Ed. J. Hines, A. Lane and M. Redknap, Land, Sea and Home: Proceedings of a Conference on Viking-Period Settlement at Cardiff, July 2001 (Leeds: 2004), 443-56.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_8_1">Owen, O. and Dalland, M., Scar: A Viking Boat Burial on Sanday, Orkney (East Linton: 1999).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_9_1">Pritchard, F. M., 'Late Saxon textiles from the City of London', Medieval Archaeology 28 (1984), 46-76.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_10_1">Pritchard, F., 'Aspects of the wool textiles from Viking Age Dublin' in Ed. L. Bender Jørgensen and E. Munksgaard, NESAT IV: Archaeological Textiles in Northern Europe (Copenhagen: 1992), 93-104.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_11_1">Salzman, L. F., English Industries of the Middle Ages (Oxford: 1923).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_12_1">Walton, P., "The textiles" in B. Harbottle and M. Ellison, 'An excavation in the castle ditch, Newcastle upon Tyne, 1974-76', Archaeologia Aeliana, 5th series 9 (1981), 190-228, 248-9.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_13_1">Walton, P., 'Medieval and 17th century textiles from High Street/Blackfriargate' in P. Armstrong and B. Ayers, 'Excavation in High Street and Blackfriargate', East Riding Archaeologist 8, Hull Old Town Report Series 5 (1987), 227-32.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_14_1">Walton, P., Textiles, Cordage and Raw Fibre from 16–22 Coppergate, The Archaeology of York 17.5 (London: 1989).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_15_1">Walton, P., 'Textiles' in Ed. J. Blair and N. Ramsay, English Medieval Industries (London: 1991), 319-54.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_16_1">Walton Rogers, P., 'The re-appearance of an old Roman loom in medieval England' in Ed. P. Walton Rogers, L. Bender Jørgensen and A. Rast-Eicher, The Roman Textile Industry and its Influence: a Birthday Tribute to John Peter Wild (Oxford: 2001), 158-71.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_17_1">Walton Rogers database: http://ads.ahds.ac.uk/catalogue/archive/clothing_eh_2007/</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-129_bibl_18_1">Walton Rogers, P., Cloth and Clothing in Early Anglo-Saxon England, AD 450-700, Council for British Archaeology Research Reports 145 (York: 2007).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
