<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xs="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns:type="application/tei+xml" xml:id="EALL-COM-0020">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">ʿArab</title>
            <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/search?query=local.names+all+%22Not Specified%22">
               <name type="person">Not Specified</name>
               <idno type="ORCID"/>
               <idno type="ISNI"/>
            </author>
            <funder ref="placeholder"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>BRILL</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Leiden | Boston</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="placeholder">Placeholder</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Arabic Language and Linguistics</title>
               <editor>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Lutz</forename>
                     <surname>Edzard</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Rudolf</forename>
                     <surname>de Jong</surname>
                  </persName>
               </editor>
               <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
               <idno type="DOI">10.1163/1570-6699_eall_EALL_COM_0020</idno>
               <idno type="sams-id">eall</idno>
               <idno type="publisher-id">EALO</idno>
               <idno type="ISBN">9789004177024</idno>
               <idno type="ISSN">1570-6699</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p><!-- <info><sumpara>The term Arab as a designation for groups of people in Arabia and adjacent areas is documented continuously from the middle of the 9th century B.C.E. until the present day. Its meaning has changed substantially during this period. Its original etymology is not clear but a suggestion will be presented below. This entry is based on an investigation of the documentation of Arabs in all pre-Islamic sources as well as the most important early Islamic ones, documented in Rets&#x00F6; (2003). The textual evidence, an analysis of it, as well as references to sources and secondary literature are found in that work.</sumpara></info> --></p>
         </abstract>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Language and Linguistics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css" schemeVersion="3.0"/>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="italic">font:italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="bold">font:bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="underline">font:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="subscript">font:subscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="superscript">font:superscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallcaps">font:smallcaps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20090831" status="first-print">Print publication</change>
         <change when="20110530" status="first-online"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">1. Pre-Islamic period</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-miṣr-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Bedouin-05"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Bedouin-06"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Tiglath_Pileser_III_King-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Ula_al-_inscription_of-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-inscription_of_al-Ula-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Namāra_inscription_of-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Salmanasar_III_King-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Nabataean_Aramaic-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-nationalism_Arab-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-qurrā_ahl_al--01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-arab_al-āriba-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Ḥuṣrī_Sāṭi_al-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Sheba_Queen_of-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-ahl_al-qurra-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Yemeni_Arabic-03"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Biqā_Valley-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-nation_Arab-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-mutaarriba-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Ḥimyaritic-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-moagaritai-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-mustariba-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Qaṭabānian-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-arabiyya-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-aṣabiyya-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-muhājirūn-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-mahgrāyē-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-ṭayyāyē-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-ajamī-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-anṣār-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-araba-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-arabes-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-arabī-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Arbāya-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Arbāya-02"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-āriba-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-bādiya-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-bādiya-02"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Medina-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-ajam-02"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-faṣīḥ-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Gesem-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Horan-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-ibrī-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-kitāb-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-mawlā-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-ridda-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-arap-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-badw-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-qurā-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-dūr-01"/>We possess rich contemporary source material, dating from the 1,400 years between the 9th century B.C.E. and the rise of Islam, mentioning <anchor xml:id="idx-Arabs-01"/>Arabs (almost 4,000 instances of the word) in <anchor xml:id="idx-Akkadian-04"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Akkadian-05"/>Akkadian, <anchor xml:id="idx-Hebrew-04"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Hebrew-05"/>Hebrew, <anchor xml:id="idx-Persian-05"/>Persian, <anchor xml:id="idx-AramaicSyriac-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Aramaic-05"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Syriac-01"/>Aramaic/Syriac, <anchor xml:id="idx-Greek-02"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Greek-03"/>Greek, <anchor xml:id="idx-Latin-03"/>Latin, and <anchor xml:id="idx-South_Arabian-01"/>South Arabian sources. Only a couple of them are certain to originate directly from the Arabs themselves. A group called <hi rendition="#italic">ar-ba-a-a</hi> (= <hi rendition="#italic">arbāya</hi>) appears for the first time among the kings of Syria in the monolith inscription of the <anchor xml:id="idx-Assyrian-01"/>Assyrian King Salmanasar III (858–824 B.C.E.), describing the battle of <anchor xml:id="idx-Qarqar-01"/>Qarqar in 853 B.C.E. In Assyrian inscriptions from the time of Tiglath Pileser III (744–727 B.C.E.) and onwards, people called <hi rendition="#italic">arab</hi> are mentioned as dwellers in the Syrian desert in and around the oasis of <anchor xml:id="idx-Dūmah-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Dūmah-02"/>Dūmah. They were the target of at least two major Assyrian attacks, under Sennacherib and Assurbanipal (Retsö 2003:124–193). The <hi rendition="#italic">arab</hi> and the <hi rendition="#italic">arbāya</hi> further occur in the inscriptions of the Achaemenid kings (Darius I, Xerxes I, Artaxerxes I) and are identified as <hi rendition="#italic">arábioi</hi> in <anchor xml:id="idx-Herodotus-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Herodotus-02"/>Herodotus (Retsö 2003:235–250). The <hi rendition="#italic">arab</hi> in the Syrian desert also appear several times in the <anchor xml:id="idx-Old_Testament-01"/>Old Testament (e.g. Jeremiah 25:18–26; Retsö 2003:212–228). Herodotus' <hi rendition="#italic">arábioi</hi> lived in the area between the eastern Nile Delta, southern Palestine, and the Sinai Peninsula (<hi rendition="#italic">Historiae</hi> 2.75, 3.5). One of their deities was <hi rendition="#italic">Alilat</hi>, in which we perhaps have the earliest documentation of an Arabic dialect with the definite article <hi rendition="#italic">(a)l</hi> (<hi rendition="#italic">Historiae</hi> 1.198, 3.8). The Arabs in this area had probably been settled there already by the Assyrians (Retsö 2003:243–250).</p>
         <p>From the time of Darius I (522–486 B.C.E.) we discern a political entity between Syria and Egypt, ruled by the Arabs described by Herodotus, which lasted until 106 C.E., when it was incorporated into the Roman provincial system as <anchor xml:id="idx-Provincia_Arabia-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Provincia_Arabia-02"/>Provincia Arabia. One of its rulers was Gešem/<anchor xml:id="idx-Gašmū_ha-arḇī-01"/>Gašmū ha-ʿarḇī ‘the Arab’, mentioned in Nehemiah (2:19, 4:7, 6:1–2), who lived in the second half of the 5th century B.C.E. (Retsö 2003:250–251). This entity, which during its later history was ruled by the kings of NBṬ, the Nabataeans, residing in present-day <anchor xml:id="idx-Petra-01"/>Petra, obviously played a central role, functioning as a cultural and economic link between the Fertile Crescent, the Mediterranean world, and the Arabian Peninsula. The language and script they used was Aramaic, but a substantial part of the population spoke dialects classifiable as Arabic. Most of the pre-Islamic documentation of a language called Arabic refers to this area (Retsö 2002:141).</p>
         <p>Other areas where we hear of groups called Arabs in pre-Islamic times are Ḥawrān, the Biqāʿ valley, central and northern Syria (around ar-Ristan, around Qinnasrin), Central Mesopotamia, and <anchor xml:id="idx-South_Arabia-01"/>South Arabia (Retsö 2003:308–358, 440–448, 536–567). In the latter two, Arabs played a crucial role after the turn of the era. In Mesopotamia they were an important factor in the state ruled from <anchor xml:id="idx-Hatra-01"/>Hatra from the 1st to the mid-3rd centuries C.E., serving as a buffer between Parthia and Rome. Arabs are mentioned in <anchor xml:id="idx-Osrhoene-01"/>Osrhoene and <anchor xml:id="idx-Adiabene-01"/>Adiabene as well, probably originating from Hatra. In South Arabia, Arabs are mentioned approximately 40 times in <anchor xml:id="idx-Sabaean-01"/>Sabaean and Qatabanian inscriptions from the period between the 1st and 6th centuries C.E. (Retsö 2003:536–566). An isolated early mention (ʿRBM) may, however, be found in the inscription RÉS 3945 by the Sabaean ruler <anchor xml:id="idx-Karibil_Watar-01"/>Karibʾil Watar, datable to the 7th or 6th century B.C.E. (Retsö 2003:537–539).</p>
         <p>The pre-Islamic evidence does not support the idea that Arab was a general designation for people living in the peninsula. Instead, they appear as groups in the above-mentioned areas living among other peoples. When sometimes used in Greek and Latin texts as a general term, it is derived from the name given to the entire peninsula, Arabia, a designation going back to the Greek discoveries in connection with the campaign of Alexander the Great. The Greek geographers from <anchor xml:id="idx-Eratosthenes-01"/>Eratosthenes onwards named the newly discovered continent Arabia, and consequently its inhabitants were sometimes called Arabs, <hi rendition="#italic">árabes</hi>, or <hi rendition="#italic">arábioi</hi>. Furthermore, the evidence does not support the idea found in most modern textbooks that Arab at this time designated nomads, Bedouin, or desert-dwellers in general. Apart from the fact that these terms do not necessarily mean the same thing, it has been pointed out that the classical Bedouin culture arose after the turn of the era, especially around the 3rd century C.E., so that the word Arab cannot refer to Bedouin of this kind since it occurs as early as the 9th century B.C.E. (Caskel 1953a, 1953b; Bulliet 1975:28–110; Knauf 1988: 9–15). The evidence shows that the Arabs in antiquity had a special relationship with the camel, documented already in their first appearance at Qarqar. According to the Assyrian evidence, the <hi rendition="#italic">arab</hi> in Dumah were ruled by priest-queens, <hi rendition="#italic">apkallatu</hi>, which is probably reflected in the legend of the Queen of Sheba in the Old Testament (Retsö 2003:173–176). From Hebrew and Greek sources we hear that they did not till the soil, they did not drink wine, they did not live in houses built from stone, they worshipped only two gods, <anchor xml:id="idx-Ruḍā-01"/>Ruḍā and <anchor xml:id="idx-Allāt-01"/>Allāt (= <anchor xml:id="idx-Alilat-01"/>Alilat), and they had their hair cropped in a special way (Jeremiah 25:25; Herodotus, <hi rendition="#italic">Historiae</hi> 3.8; Diodorus 19.94.2–95.2; Diodorus’ original text speaks about Arabs only, not Nabataeans, cf. Retsö 2003:285–289). On the Assyrian reliefs one can see that they were dressed in a short loincloth, like the<hi rendition="#italic">ʾizār</hi> of the present-day pilgrims to Mecca. They thus seem to constitute a distinct group of their own among the inhabitants of Arabia.</p>
         <p>It is striking that they almost always appear in military contexts even if their weaponry seems to have been quite primitive. They were, however, amply used as auxiliary troops, border guards, and police forces by the empires. The occurrence of two forms of the designation for them may be connected with this. The Assyrians fought against <hi rendition="#italic">arab</hi> but their employees are mostly called <hi rendition="#italic">arbāya</hi>. Likewise, in South Arabia the enemies of the Sabaean and Himyarite kings are ʿRB, whereas their auxiliaries, allies, and border guards are usually called ʾʿRB. <hi rendition="#italic">Arbāya</hi> is a <hi rendition="#italic">nisba</hi> adjective from the collective noun <hi rendition="#italic">arab</hi> and ʾʿRB is a plural of the Sabaean <hi rendition="#italic">nisba</hi> ʿRBY. The Arabs employed by the empires often stood under a special command represented by an officer, a KBR in South Arabia, an <hi rendition="#italic">arabárkhes</hi> in Egypt, <anchor xml:id="idx-Nabataea-01"/>Nabataea, and Syria and a RBYTʾ or a ŠLṬʾ in Hatra and Osrhoene (Retsö 2003:409–411). Finally, <hi rendition="#italic">arábioi</hi> appear in a great mythical scene in <anchor xml:id="idx-Nonnos-01"/>Nonnos' <hi rendition="#italic">Dionysiaca</hi>, written in the 5th century C.E. but deriving from a Greek text from ca. 400 B.C.E. In this epic the Arabs constitute the entourage of the semi-divine hero Lycurgus fighting against Dionysus, the god of wine. The myth itself originated in southern Syria where both Lycurgus and Arab presence are well documented in texts and inscriptions from late antiquity (Retsö 2003:610–614).</p>
         <p>The picture of the pre-Islamic Arabs is thus somewhat reminiscent of that of the <anchor xml:id="idx-Rechabites-01"/>Rechabites and the <anchor xml:id="idx-Levites-01"/>Levites in the Old Testament. Even if the Rechabites in some way lived like nomads they were not typical nomads. The Arabs may originally have been a similar group, for whom the nomadic way of living was due to explicit ruling and ideology, not to economic necessity. There are no traces among them of the elaborate tribal system found in the later Arabo-Islamic sources. As a matter of fact, we do not hear of specific Arab tribes at all.</p>
         <p>A special case is the group called <anchor xml:id="idx-Qidru-01"/>Qidru or <anchor xml:id="idx-Qadru-01"/>Qadru in Assyrian texts and <anchor xml:id="idx-Qedar-01"/>Qedar in the Old Testament They seem to have had a unique relationship with the <hi rendition="#italic">arab</hi> in Dūmah from the 8th century B.C.E. onwards and their kings are called king of Qedar or king of Arabs. The same double designation is found with the kings of Nabataea who mostly appear as kings of the <hi rendition="#italic">árabes</hi> in Greek sources but as MLK NBṬ in the inscriptions and coins from Nabataea. From Greek, Latin, and Talmudic sources it appears that Arabs and Nabataeans were not identical (Retsö 2003:312–314, 397, 527, 528). There are also hints at a close relationship between Qedar and the rulers of Nabataea: Qedar appears to dwell in the same area from the 5th century B.C.E. (Knauf 1985:96–108). The parallel between Arabs and Qedar/Nabataeans is unique and points to a special social and political structure in the regions east and south of Palestine during a long period.</p>
         <p>A remarkable fact is that the term Arab disappears from North Arabia from ca. 300 C.E. onwards. The Namara inscription from 328 C.E. is, in fact, the last major testimony of Arabs in the Syrian desert. The ruler mentioned in it, <anchor xml:id="idx-Imru_al-Qays-01"/>Imruʾ al-Qays ibn ʿAmr, ‘king of all Arabs’, seems to have ruled Arabs in southern Syria and along the Roman Limes up to Osrhoene and taken part in a major military operation to South Arabia (see analysis and discussion in Retsö 2003:467–485). In the 4th century Arabs are replaced by <anchor xml:id="idx-Saracens-01"/>Saracens in the Greek-Latin sources and by <hi rendition="#italic">ṭayyāyē</hi> in the Syriac ones (Retsö 2003:505–521). There are numerous passages in Greek, Syriac, and Talmudic sources showing that these two were considered separate from the Arabs (e.g. Retsö 2003:487–491, 517–520). The disappearance of the Arabs from the sources could thus indicate the disappearance of the people so named, which supports the assumption that Arabs were a social or religious institution rather than being representative of a way of living or a genealogically defined group. It has been assumed that major changes took place in North Arabia in the 3rd century C.E., caused by the introduction of new weaponry from Iran (Caskel 1953a, 1953b; Bulliet 1975:100–105), and the disappearance of the Arabs in this period may thus be connected with this process. Classical Bedouin culture arose in connection with these changes, which means that it was not Arab in the old sense of the word.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">2. The Islamic period</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The study of the Arabs in the Islamic period is complicated by the problematic source situation for the most crucial period, viz. between the time of the Prophet and the fall of the Umayyads. Almost all relevant sources are written after the fall of the Umayyad dynasty and the analysis of them and their trustworthiness constitutes a major problem. In the poetry ascribed to the preIslamic poets there are astonishingly few mentions of the word Arab. This confirms the picture of the disappearance of the Arabs in non-Arabic sources from late antiquity and is, in fact, an argument in favor of the genuineness of the poetry. In the <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi>, the word <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> does not occur. The adjective <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarabiyy</hi> is found on eleven occasions in the Meccan suras, always, it seems, referring to the language of the Revelation. The word <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi> occurs in ten passages in the Medinan suras (Q. 33/20, 48/11, 16; 9/90, 97–101, 120). The <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi> are criticized for not having performed their duties as participants in military operations undertaken by the <hi rendition="#italic">muhājirūn</hi>, the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾanṣār</hi>, and ‘those who followed them’ (Q. 9/100–101) According to Q. 33/20 they live in the <hi rendition="#italic">bādiya</hi>, a word which most likely originally means the land outside a main, usually walled city, in this case most probably <anchor xml:id="idx-Yathrib-01"/>Yathrib/Medina (cf. <anchor xml:id="idx-Ibn_Xaldūn-01"/>Ibn Xaldūn, <hi rendition="#italic">Muqaddima</hi> 1,2).</p>
         <p>From several statements in the later literature it seems clear that the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi> were people of subordinate status to city-dwellers or the Muslim community with a duty to take part in warfare, a picture conforming to the one in the <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi> (Retsö 2003:82–87, against Marbach 1992). All inhabitants of the <hi rendition="#italic">bādiya</hi> were thus not necessarily ʾʿRB, who look very similar to the ʾʿRB in the Sabaean texts. It might be surmised that, indeed, <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi> is a loanword from South Arabia. The parallel function of the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi> in the <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi> and the ʾʿRB in the South Arabian inscriptions might indicate that they were a similar kind of institution, perhaps originating in South Arabia. Later on, in Islamic literature <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi> is used as a general designation for people living as shepherds outside the sown area and becomes more a synonym of our term Bedouin.</p>
         <p>As far as the word <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> is concerned, it is used with several different meanings in the Arabo-Islamic literature, especially when referring to the time of the Prophet and the 1st Islamic century. It may be used as a comprehensive term for all the Muslims, i.e. the tribesmen and their associates, in other words the citizens of the Umayyad Empire (Retsö 2003:63ff.). It can designate the full tribesman as opposed to the <hi rendition="#italic">mawlā</hi> ‘client’, who could be a tribesman from another tribe (or a non-tribesman, Retsö 2003:69ff.). On several occasions, it is used for the <hi rendition="#italic">muhājirūn</hi>, sometimes including the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾanṣār</hi>, i.e. the kernel troops of the Islamic movement, whereas the <anchor xml:id="idx-Qurayš-02"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Qurayš-03"/>Qurayš of Mecca are often contrasted with the <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi>. It also seems to have been used by the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾanṣār</hi> and their Yemeni allies as a designation for themselves opposed to other groups (Retsö 2003:71–76).</p>
         <p>From this usage the idea developed that the Yemenis and the<hi rendition="#italic">ʾanṣār</hi> were the ‘real Arabs’, <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʿarab al-ʿāriba</hi>, a concept that can be traced to the beginning of the 8th century C.E., when the influence of these two groups was waning (Retsö 2003:28–40). This idea had a deep impact on historiography and is reproduced by the genealogical system found in most Islamic historical works. This latter case shows that the term <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> in the 1st Islamic century was a term with political and ideological importance due to some kind of prestige. From the contemporary, non-Arabic evidence from the 1st Islamic century it can be seen that the original designation for the Muslim army and the Islamic state was <hi rendition="#italic">muhājirūn</hi>, Syriac <hi rendition="#italic">mahgrāyē</hi>, Greek <hi rendition="#italic">moagarîtai</hi>, but that the term Arab, Greek <hi rendition="#italic">árabes</hi>, was introduced in the latter half of the Umayyad period (Retsö 2003:96–99).</p>
         <p>Apart from these usages, which are widely spread in Arabic historiography, there are traces of further employments of the word <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi>. Quite often it seems to designate a section of a tribe or people somehow attached to a tribe. An expression like <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab Kināna</hi> may well mean Arabs coming from, being attached to, or being a part of the Kināna tribe (Retsö 2003:76ff.). A similar usage is found in pre-Islamic South Arabian inscriptions, in which expressions like ʾʿRB KDT ‘the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi> of <anchor xml:id="idx-Kinda-01"/>Kinda' parallels ʾʿRB SBʾ ‘the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi> of Saba’ or ʾʿRB ḤḌRMWT the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi> of Ḥaḍramawt (Jamme 1962:665.2; Iryani 1990:323; Robin and Gajda 1994:7.13; see Retsö 2003:552–553, 555). In the latter cases, there can be no doubt about the difference between the ʾʿRB and the ‘mother nations’ like Kinda, and a similar distinction can be claimed for Central and North Arabia. It is, however, to be observed that in this context the Islamic sources usually employ the term <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> rather than <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi>, although there clear indications that the distinction between the two was often blurred in the Arabic tradition (Retsö 2003:80, n. 30). It is remarkable that the non-Arabic sources do not know the word <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi>, a term which seems to have been forgotten early. The difference between ʿRB and ʾʿRB in South Arabia is reminiscent of the one between <hi rendition="#italic">arab</hi> and <hi rendition="#italic">arbāya</hi> in the Akkadian texts (cf. also Retsö 2003:5 for the difference between <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> and <hi rendition="#italic">ʿurbān</hi> in contemporary Arabia).</p>
         <p>Another deviant use of the word Arab is found in connection with the term <hi rendition="#italic">al-qurā l-ʿarabiyya</hi> ‘the villages (even cities) of the Arabs’. This expression seems above all to be connected with the area around present-day al-ʿUla. One source defines them as the towns of <anchor xml:id="idx-Xaybar-01"/>Xaybar, <anchor xml:id="idx-Fadak-01"/>Fadak, as-<anchor xml:id="idx-Suwāriqiyya-01"/>Suwāriqiyya, and some others, which are sites around that area. Another passage refers to the sites around Dūmah. Several scholars have assumed a connection between this concept and the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾahl al-qurrāʾ</hi> who appear in the earliest phase of Islamic history: the Biʾr Maʿūna incident, the <hi rendition="#italic">ridda</hi> wars, and some events during the reign of <hi rendition="#italic">al-xulafāʾ ar-rāšidūn</hi> (see Retsö 2003:61, n. 166 for references). These people were known as readers of the Qurʾānic text but apparently also as connected with these <hi rendition="#italic">qurā</hi>. The exact meaning of this is not yet clear but it is worthwhile comparing it with the statements in later sources that the <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> are people living in fortified cities (<hi rendition="#italic">ʾamṣār</hi>, Retsö 2003:48–51). Even if this partly reflects the conditions in the conquered lands in the 1st Islamic century, we still have an obscure tradition that Arabs are connected with a special kind of town or settlement, which corresponds well with much of the pre-Islamic evidence. In Assyrian and Achaemenid times several Arab settlements (<hi rendition="#italic">dūr</hi>) in Mesopotamia are mentioned. Arabs are also connected with the town of Hatra and, probably, with <anchor xml:id="idx-Hagar-01"/>Hagar in Eastern Arabia, present-day al-<anchor xml:id="idx-Hufūf-01"/>Hufūf (Retsö 2003:168, 304–305, 307, 449, 434–453).</p>
         <p>The many contradictory usages of the word Arab found in Arabo-Islamic literature are an important fact and may be interpreted plausibly as reflecting a historical development in the period from the time of the Prophet to the fall of the Umayyads. It seems that the comprehensive meanings of the word are later than the more limited references. This is also compatible with the disappearance of the word from the sources of late antiquity and its preservation in South Arabian ones. The settlement of Arabs in special, limited regions, on the one hand, and the function of the <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿrāb</hi>, manifest in the Arabic sources, on the other, fits well the picture found in the South Arabian texts, which show a similar difference between ʿRB and ʾʿRB.</p>
         <p>Their absence from the <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi> corresponds with the picture gleaned from pre-Islamic poetry that Arabs were not an important group in the environment where these texts were composed. But it seems that the designation received a renewed importance during the early period of the caliphate. It was used both by the Yemenis/<hi rendition="#italic">ʾanṣār</hi> and the emerging tribal aristocracy as a self-designation. In the latter half of the Umayyad period, it was used as a term for all warriors and, eventually, for all members of the Islamic state. The classic view of the Arabs as the tribes that constituted the empire of the Umayyads and their descendants, as well as the distinction between the Yemeni branch of these tribes, <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʿarab al-ʿāriba</hi>, and the Ishmaelite branch, <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʿarab al-mustaʿriba</hi> or <hi rendition="#italic">al-mutaʿarriba</hi>, seems to have been established in the latter half of the Umayyad period, perhaps during the reign of ʿUmar ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz (717–720; cf. Dagorn 1981:208–209, 217).</p>
         <p>The application of the term <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> to the Yemenis shows very clearly that it was a term that could be used for political and ideological purposes and that its meaning was not a self-evident fact. In pre-Islamic times, for instance, there was a clear difference between Arabs and the peoples of Yemen, a difference which was thus abolished by this new politically conditioned definition. The main factor is its transformation from a designation of an institution to a characteristic of members of a tribal society during the time of the first Islamic empire. The use of <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> as a designation for the Muslims lost its meaning after the fall of the Umayyad dynasty. It seems, however, that the term from then on had been adopted definitely by the tribes as a designation for themselves. The extent of its use among the tribes during the Islamic Middle Ages is, however, still uninvestigated. The present-day usage may give a clue (see below).</p>
         <p>The multifarious usages of the term Arab in the sources dealing with the early Islamic period is reflected in the entries on <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> in the great medieval dictionaries, from al-Xalīl's <hi rendition="#italic">Kitāb al-ʿayn</hi> via al-ʾAzharī's <hi rendition="#italic">at- Tahḏīb fī l-luġa</hi> and Ibn Manẓūr's <hi rendition="#italic">Lisān al-ʿarab</hi> to az-Zabīdī's <hi rendition="#italic">Tāj al-ʿarūs</hi>. These entries, which largely tend to copy each other, preserve the many contradictory meanings of the word and should be read with this fact in mind. In his <hi rendition="#italic">Muqaddima</hi>, Ibn Xaldūn defines the people of the <hi rendition="#italic">badw</hi> as those who dwell outside the cities, making their living as peasants or shepherds. The harder the living conditions, the stronger the sense of blood ties. The most extreme of these are the <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi>, who dwell under the most severe conditions of all, and for whom tribal solidarity built on blood ties (<hi rendition="#italic">ʿaṣabiyya</hi>) is the main factor of identity. The <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> are thus a section of the <hi rendition="#italic">badw</hi>, the people of the <hi rendition="#italic">bādiya</hi> or the Bedouin, characterized by the all-encompassing importance of genealogical relations. This means that not all Bedouin are <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> (Ibn Xaldūn I, 2/Rosenthal 1958:I, 249 ff.).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">3. The modern period</hi>
         </p>
         <p>During the last two centuries there have been basically two definitions of Arabs. The first is the one used by many of the tribes in Arabia and North Africa and their settled relatives, distinguishing them from other people, sedentary or nomads. The main criterion for being an Arab according to this definition is the possession of an accepted genealogy, making it possible to trace one's ancestors back to some famous forebear and/or ultimately back to the tribes of Arabia at the time of the Prophet. This definition is widespread and well-documented through modern texts collected from informants (Retsö 2003:1–7). It seems that it is quite old, closely related to Ibn Xaldūn's description and traceable even to the earliest Arabic sources as one of the meanings occurring there. It can be assumed that it originated in the Umayyad period. An <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> is thus a tribesman with his genealogy in good order, be he a nomad or a sedentary (one might compare the use of the term <hi rendition="#italic">arap</hi> in Afghanistan for tribes that do not speak Arabic but trace themselves back genealogically to the peninsula; cf. Kieffer 1980).</p>
         <p>The other definition is the one launched by the ideologists behind the modern Arab nationalist movements. The criteria are diverse but as a rule rather vague: common language, common culture, common history, sometimes even a common ancestry. It is ultimately based on the romantic European concepts of nationhood (Choueiri 2000). This definition, developed during the last decades of the 19th century, was proclaimed to a wide public for the first time by N. Azoury in his <hi rendition="#italic">Le réveil de la nation arabe</hi> (1905; see Hourani 1970:277–279). At this time the extent of ‘the Arab nation’ had not yet been precisely defined, and Azoury excluded the whole of North Africa. The concept of the Arab nation turned out to be very useful as a main ideological weapon in the struggle against the European colonial powers after the First World War. The political dominance of Great Britain and France in the Middle East and North Africa is perhaps the main factor behind the creation of the modern Arab nation, which also has transformed the citizens of the modern states into Arabs. Eventually, the pan-Arab ideology was made politically manifest in the creation of the <anchor xml:id="idx-Arab_League-01"/>Arab League in 1946. The influence of the new concept of Arabism culminated ideologically in the writings of Sāṭiʿ al-Ḥuṣrī (d. 1949) and politically with the career of Gamāl ʿAbd an-Nāṣir, who tried to implement the idea by taking the first steps toward creating a pan-Arab political structure. The failure of Nāṣir's political project, combined with the repeated defeats of the Arab states by <anchor xml:id="idx-Israel-01"/>Israel has diminished the practical importance of the Arab ideology, although it still plays an important role in political rhetoric. Its most important result is, apart from the abolition of foreign political control in the Arab world, the revivification of the <hi rendition="#italic">
                     <ref target="EALL-SIM-0008">ʿarabiyya</ref>
                  </hi> language and its introduction as the official language in 18 states from the Atlantic to Oman. A widespread sense of belonging to an Arab nation, independent of the borders of the modern Arab states, bound together by a common language and cultural heritage, is also a lasting result of the modern Arab nationalist movement.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">4. The language of the Arabs</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A distinction should be made between the linguistic data from Arabia and adjacent regions, which by modern linguists are classified as Arabic, and the explicit characterization of a language in the ancient sources, pre-Islamic and Islamic, as Arabic. In Greek and Latin pre-Islamic sources there is a handful of references to an Arabic language, <hi rendition="#italic">arabikē glōssa, arabikē diálektos</hi>, the <hi rendition="#italic">phōnē</hi> of the <hi rendition="#italic">árabes, arabicus sermo</hi>, and <hi rendition="#italic">arabica lingua</hi> (Retsö 2003:591). The earliest one is found in <anchor xml:id="idx-Agatharchides-01"/>Agatharchides' description of the Red Sea, written ca. 140 B.C.E., mentioning the name of a plant, <hi rendition="#italic">lárimna</hi>, as <hi rendition="#italic">arabistí</hi>. In the <anchor xml:id="idx-Talmud-01"/>Talmud there are approximately 30 words which are said to be used by Arabs or to derive from Arabia (Retsö 2002). Most of the occurrences date from after the turn of the era and refer to a language/languages in and around the Provincia Arabia. The only definite exception is a notice in the <hi rendition="#italic">Periplus Maris Erythraei</hi> (ca. 70 C.E.) about ‘holy men’ on the island of <anchor xml:id="idx-Sarapis-01"/>Sarapis, i.e. present-day <anchor xml:id="idx-Masira-01"/>Masira, using an <hi rendition="#italic">arabikē glōssa</hi>. The exact nature of this/these language(s) escapes us. The words in the Talmud are varied and only a few of them are recognizable as Arabic according to later standards.</p>
         <p>The Qurʾānic passages referring to an Arabic language all deal with the oral performance of the text, <hi rendition="#italic">al-Qurʾān</hi>, and seem to distinguish this from the writing, <hi rendition="#italic">al-kitāb</hi>. They occur in contexts where the authority of the revelation is at stake, in which the Arabic character of the recitation is adduced as proof that the text is indeed of divine origin. The <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarabī</hi> language thus seems in some way to have been associated with speech from the non-human world. The opposite term for <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarabī</hi> in the <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi> is <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿjamī</hi>, a term originally meaning ‘crooked’, ‘twisted’, in a linguistic sense (Q. 41/44, 26/198–199, 16/103). In later Arabic lexicography the term <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿjamī</hi> contrasted with <hi rendition="#italic">
                     <ref target="EALL-COM-vol2-0014">faṣīḥ</ref>
                  </hi>. The lexicographers make a distinction between <hi rendition="#italic">ʾaʿjam</hi> ‘non-<hi rendition="#italic">faṣīḥ</hi>’, and <hi rendition="#italic">ʿajam</hi>, ‘foreigner, non-Arab’, especially Iranians, but this distinction is probably secondary (Retsö 2003:24–28). The lexicographers sometimes identify <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> and <hi rendition="#italic">faṣīḥ</hi>, but mostly state that one can be <hi rendition="#italic">faṣīḥ</hi> without being <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarabī</hi> (<hi rendition="#italic">Lisān al-ʿarab</hi>, s.v. <hi rendition="#italic">ʿJM</hi>). This would mean that the Arab identity was not dependent on linguistic criteria. This raises the problem why the language was called Arabic in the <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi>, which is not quite clear yet. The connection between the Arabs as they appear in the 1st Islamic century and the language of the <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi> thus remains more obscure than usually realized. It is, however, clear that, at least until the beginning of the 9th century C.E., there were people among the tribes who had a competence in the language of the <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi> through their knowledge of the language of the poetry. The early grammarians often refer to informants called <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi>. The often adduced claim about the linguistic excellence of the Qurayš in Mecca, found in many medieval works, is based on theology and ideology rather than historical and linguistic facts.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">5. Etymology</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Many etymological explanations of the word <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> have been suggested, none of which are quite convincing. An explanation found in the Middle Ages is that the name is derived from the word <hi rendition="#italic">ʿaraba</hi>, the name of a region (<hi rendition="#italic">Lisan al-ʿarab</hi> s.v. ʿRB; Retsö 2003:52–53). There is, however, no immediate connection between the areas called ʿAraba (part of the Jordan valley, possibly an area near Mecca) and the Arabs of the sources. Explanations based on the assumption of metathesis of a root ʿBR ‘pass by’, sometimes linking it with <hi rendition="#italic">ʿibrī</hi> ‘Hebrew’, ascribing to it the meaning ‘passer-by’, i.e. ‘nomad’, can be dismissed.</p>
         <p>An explanation connecting <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> with a root meaning ‘to be mixed’ is perhaps closer to the truth (Lane 1863–93 s.v. ʿRB). It could explain the opposite meaning found in <hi rendition="#italic">
                     <anchor xml:id="idx-murib-01"/>muʿrib, <anchor xml:id="idx-ārib-01"/>ʿārib</hi> ‘pure, unmixed’, which is well documented as a characterization of the <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarabiyya</hi> language or of someone speaking it. The polarity of meanings in a root is well known in Semitic languages. It is, however, doubtful whether this is the original meaning of the designation for the groups of people concerned. The concern for genealogical purity is well known among the traditional <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> today, but since the genealogical definition of an Arab seems to have risen quite late (end of the Umayyad period), genealogical purity cannot have been the original meaning of the term. The identification of the earliest Arabs as a kind of religious community dedicated to a deity or a divine hero might provide an explanation of a different kind. The root ʿRB is well known in the meaning ‘enter’ (with a variant ĠRB) from which ‘mix’ can be derived. In Ancient South Arabia ʿRB is well documented in the meaning ‘offer’, ‘give’, ‘dedicate to a god’. With this is connected the meaning ‘give a pledge or security’ from which the Arabic nouns <hi rendition="#italic">
                     <anchor xml:id="idx-arabūn-01"/>ʿarabūn, <anchor xml:id="idx-urbān-01"/>
                     <anchor xml:id="idx-urbān-02"/>ʿurbān</hi>, the Hebrew <hi rendition="#italic">ʿerabōn</hi>, and the Syriac <hi rendition="#italic">ʿrābā</hi> are formed. This word was borrowed at an early stage into Greek as <hi rendition="#italic">arrabōn</hi> ‘pledge, security’ (cf. also Latin <hi rendition="#italic">arrabo</hi>). When Herodotus describes the initiation ceremony of the <hi rendition="#italic">arábioi</hi> he characterizes it by a Greek word, <hi rendition="#italic">pístis</hi>, which may also mean ‘pledge’, ‘guarantee’. To this may be added the many instances in Akkadian where forms of this root are used to designate people and things standing in various kinds of dependency on others: thus <hi rendition="#italic">ērib bītim</hi> ‘temple official’, <hi rendition="#italic">ana ilkim erēbum</hi> ‘become vassal to someone’, <hi rendition="#italic">ana libbi adê erēbum</hi> ‘to swear an oath, <hi rendition="#italic">ana mārūtīšu erēbum</hi> ‘to be adopted by someone’, etc. (Retsö 2003:597). Both Akkadian and <anchor xml:id="idx-Ugaritic-02"/>Ugaritic know the noun <hi rendition="#italic">erbum</hi>/ʿRBM ‘gift to a temple’.</p>
         <p>All these meanings can be connected with the concept of ‘entering’, i.e. ‘entering into a dependency upon someone’. It is to be noticed that the use of the root ʿRB in these specialized meanings is found in the earliest Semitic languages, a use which is not alive in the <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarabiyya</hi>, showing that it is an archaic survival in that language. The word <hi rendition="#italic">ʿarab</hi> would then be a <hi rendition="#italic">qatal</hi> formation of a verb originally serving as an abstract or verbal noun and then as an infinitive. Starting from these functions, it could be used as a collective noun designating those who were involved in the process designated by the verb. This structure can still be seen in a few Arabic words of the same pattern such as <hi rendition="#italic">ṭalab</hi> ‘search’; ‘searchers’ (from <hi rendition="#italic">ṭalaba/yaṭlubu</hi> ‘to search’), <hi rendition="#italic">ḥaras</hi> ‘guarding’; ‘guards’ (from <hi rendition="#italic">ḥarasa/yaḥrusu</hi> ‘to guard’); <hi rendition="#italic">ġalab</hi>, ‘noise’; ‘noisy ones’ (from <hi rendition="#italic">ġalaba/yaġlibu</hi> ‘to be noisy’).</p>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Diodorus_of_Sicily-01"><title level="m">Diodorus of Sicily. Trans. C.H. Oldfather. 12 vols</title><biblScope unit="page">1933–1967</biblScope><pubPlace>London, New York and Cambridge, Mass.: Loeb</pubPlace><publisher>Classical Library</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_2_1d1e898"><author><name>Herodotus, Historiae. Trans. A.D. Godly. Cambridge, Mass. and</name></author><title level="m"/><biblScope unit="page">1920–1981</biblScope><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Loeb Classical Library</publisher></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_3_1d1e907"><author><name>Manẓūr, Ibn and al-ʿArab, Lisān</name></author><title level="m">vols</title><biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope><pubPlace>Cairo</pubPlace><publisher>Dār</publisher><unclear>Ibn Manẓūr, Lisān al-ʿArab.  . :  al-Maʿārif, n.d.</unclear><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_4_1d1e916"><title level="m">Ibn Xaldūn, Muqaddima = The Muqaddimah. An introduction to history. Trans. Franz Rosenthal</title><date>1958</date><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Routledge and Kegan Paul</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_5_1d1e928"><title level="a">RÉS = Répertoire d'épigraphie sémitique, vols</title><title level="j">V–VII. Paris</title><biblScope unit="page">1928–1950</biblScope><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Azoury_Negib-01"><author><name>Azoury, Negib</name></author><title level="m">Le réveil de la nation arabe dans l'Asie turque: En présence des intérêts et des rivalités des puissances étrangéres, de la curie romaine et du patriarcat œcuménique</title><date>1905</date><pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace><publisher>Plon</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_7_1d1e949"><author><name>Bulliet, Richard</name></author><title level="m">The camel and the wheel</title><date>1975</date><pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass. and London</pubPlace><publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_8_1d1e958"><author><name>Caskel, Werner. 1953a. Die</name></author><title level="m">Bedeutung der Beduinen für die Geschichte der Araber. Opladen and Cologne</title><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_9_1d1e967"><author><name>Caskel, Werner. 1953a. Die. 1953b</name></author><title level="m">“Zur Beduinisierung Arabiens”. Zeitschrift der Deutschen</title><date>28.*28–*36.</date><publisher>Morgenländischen Gesellschaft</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_10_1d1e976"><author><name>Choueiri, Youssef M.</name></author><title level="m">Arab nationalism: A history. Oxford and</title><date>2000</date><pubPlace>Malden, Mass</pubPlace><publisher>Blackwell</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_11_1d1e985"><author><name>Dagorn, René</name></author><title level="m">La geste d'Ismaël d'après l'onomastique et la tradition arabes. Geneva and Paris: Librairie Droz and Librairie Champion</title><date>1981</date><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_12_1d1e995"><author><name>Hourani, Albert</name></author><title level="m">Arabic thought in the liberal age 1798–1939</title><date>1967</date><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_13_1d1e1004"><author><name>Iryani</name></author><title level="m">Muṭahhar ʿAbd ar-Raḥmān al-</title><date>1990</date><pubPlace>Sanaʾ</pubPlace><unclear>, . . Nuqūš musnadiyya wa-taʿlīqāt. 2nd. ed. .</unclear><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_14_1d1e1013"><author><name>Jamme, Albert</name></author><title level="m">Sabaean inscriptions from Mahram Bilqîs (Mârib)</title><date>1962</date><pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace><publisher>Johns Hopkins Press</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_15_1d1e1022"><author><name>Kieffer, Charles M.</name></author><title level="m">“L'arabe et les arabophones de Bactriane (Afghanistan). I. Situation ethnique et linguistique”. Welt des Islams 20.178–196</title><date>1980</date><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_16_1d1e1031"><author><name>Knauf, E.A.</name></author><title level="m">Ismael: Untersuchungen zur Geschichte Palästinas und Nordarabiens im 1. Jahrtausend v. Chr</title><date>1985</date><pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace><publisher>O. Harrassowitz</publisher><unclear>Knauf, E. A. . . : .</unclear><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_17_1d1e1040"><author><name>Knauf, E.A.</name></author><title level="m">Midian: Untersuchungen zur Geschichte Palästinas und Nordarabiens am Ende des 2. Jahrtausends v. Chr</title><date>1988</date><pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace><publisher>O. Harrassowitz</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_18_1d1e1050"><author><name>Lane, Edward William. 1863–1893</name></author><title level="m"/><pubPlace>London: Williams</pubPlace><publisher>and Norgate</publisher><unclear>. Arabic–English lexicon. 8 vols.  .</unclear></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_19_1d1e1059"><author><name>Marbach, Amikam</name></author><title level="m">“Maʿnā l-muṣṭalaḥ ʿarab ḥasb al-maʿājim wa-l-Qurʾān wa-l-Kitāb li-Sībawayhi wa-Muqaddimat Ibn Xaldūn”. al-Karmil</title><biblScope unit="page">13–145</biblScope><date>1992</date><unclear>. .  13.145–178.</unclear><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Retsö_Jan-01"><author><name>Retsö, Jan</name></author><title level="m">“Das Arabische der vorislamischen Zeit bei klassischen und orientalischen Autoren”. Neue Beiträge zur Semitistik. Erstes Arbeitstreffen der Arbeitsgemeinschaft Semitistik in der Deutschen Morgenländischen</title><biblScope unit="page">139–146</biblScope><editor><name>der Friedrich-Schiller-Universität JenaNorbert Nebes</name></editor><date>2002-09-13</date><pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace><publisher>O. Harrassowitz</publisher><unclear>. 2002.  Gesellschaft vom 11. bis zum 13. September 2000 and der Friedrich-Schiller-Universität Jena, ed. Norbert Nebes, . : .</unclear><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_21_1d1e1088"><author><name>Retsö, Jan</name></author><title level="m">2003. The Arabs in antiquity: Their history from the Assyrians to the Umayyads</title><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Routledge Curzon</publisher><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-0020_bibl_22_1d1e1097"><author><name>Robin, Christian and Gajda, Iwona</name></author><title level="m">L'inscription du Wadi ʿAbadan</title><date>1994</date><unclear>Robin, Christian and Iwona Gajda. . “”. Raydan 6.113–137.</unclear><idno type="DOI"/></bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
