<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xs="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns:type="application/tei+xml" xml:id="e1122110">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Stamped ware</title>
            <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/search?query=local.names+all+%22Docter, Roald Fritjof (Amsterdam)%22">
               <name type="person">Docter, Roald Fritjof (Amsterdam)</name>
               <idno type="ORCID"/>
               <idno type="ISNI"/>
            </author>
            <funder ref="placeholder"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>BRILL</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Leiden | Boston</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="placeholder">Placeholder</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">Brill’s New Pauly</title>
               <editor>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Hubert</forename>
                     <surname>Cancik and </surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Helmuth </forename>
                     <surname>Schneider</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>English Edition by: Christine F.</forename>
                     <surname>Salazar</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Classical Tradition volumes edited by: Manfred</forename>
                     <surname>Landfester</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>English Edition by: Francis G. </forename>
                     <surname>Gentry</surname>
                  </persName>
               </editor>
               <biblScope unit="volume"/>
               <biblScope unit="page">13:783-785</biblScope>
               <idno type="DOI">10.1163/1574-9347_bnp_e1122110</idno>
               <idno type="sams-id">bnp</idno>
               <idno type="publisher-id">NPOE</idno>
               <idno type="ISSN">1574-9347</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Classical Studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css" schemeVersion="3.0"/>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="italic">font:italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="bold">font:bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="underline">font:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="subscript">font:subscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="superscript">font:superscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallcaps">font:smallcaps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20110510" status="first-print">Print publication</change>
         <change when="20061001" status="first-online"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>
                  <ref type="NPOG" target="e1122110">[German version]</ref>
               </p>
         <p>Almost all cultures produced pottery decorated by stamping, <hi rendition="#italic">e.g</hi>. the Greek <ref type="NPOE" target="e926390">pithos</ref>, the Etruscan <ref type="NPOE" target="e523660">impasto</ref> and <ref type="NPOE" target="e220880">bucchero</ref>. In the narrower sense, the archaeological term SW refers to the types of stamped vessels of the Hellenistic and Roman periods, esp. <ref type="NPOE" target="e1105420">black-glaze ware</ref> and sigillata pottery of Late Antiquity from North Africa (<ref type="NPOE" target="e1204690">Terra sigillata</ref>).</p>
         <p>The practice of stamping vessels was introduced in black-glaze ware at Athens around the mid 5th cent. BC [1]. In particular, stamped vessels included palmettes, ivy and olive leaves, meanders, inscribed triangles and diamonds. From the late 4th cent. BC, the stamping repertoire became restricted to palmettes in connection with wheel-stamp decorations. SW lost its primacy at Athens around 225 BC to moulded vessels (<ref type="NPOE" target="e1020750">Relief ware</ref>), but continued to be produced until around the mid-2nd cent. [2]. The stamps themselves were manufactured in a mould and had a rounded surface, enabling the stamps to be applied both on flat and curved vessel elements using a rotary hand movement, before the black glaze was applied [3].</p>
         <p>One of the most important genres of SW in the West was manufactured at Rome or in its immediate environs, and in Etruria (<hi rendition="#italic">e.g</hi>. <ref type="NPOE" target="e1004870">Populonia</ref>): the so-called <hi rendition="#italic">Groupe</hi> (formerly <hi rendition="#italic">Atelier</hi>) <hi rendition="#italic">des Petites Estampilles</hi> [4. 1, 59-117; 5. 243-246]. Its typical product are simple bowls (<hi rendition="#italic">pocula</hi>) bearing four small stamps in the centre on parallel axes. There are also examples with one, three or five stamps, which are often impressions of seal stones (<hi rendition="#italic">e.g</hi>. palmettes, rosettes). Coin images from the time of the Roman <ref type="NPOE" target="e106130">
                     aes grave
                  </ref> issues can also be found among the stamp motifs (helmeted Athena, open right and left hands, dolphins, Pegasus and clam shells). The workshops were active from <hi rendition="#italic">c</hi>. 300 to 260 BC, and evidently specialized to a high degree in the export trade. The main production is from a short time span from 285 to 265 BC. The different genres thus represent a kind of chronological ‘index fossil’ for the period immediately preceding the first <ref type="NPOE" target="e1014630">Punic War</ref>. It was probably due to Massaliot traders (<ref type="NPOE" target="e725870">Massalia</ref>) that SW was distributed across southern France and the coast of the Spanish Levant [6], while other agents must be assumed for the spread to Carthage and North Africa [7; 4. 101-103, fig. 27]. Rome or its environs produced another genre of SW around 200 BC: the ‘Hercules bowls’ named after their typical seal stone representations [8; 9].</p>
         <p>A third genre of SW in the West was black-glaze ware of the ‘Campana A’ type from the region of Naples. It dates from the 2nd half of the 3rd cent. BC to the 1st cent. BC, and was widely distributed across the Mediterranean, esp. in the 2nd cent. BC [10; 9; 5. 246-249]. Stamps of rosettes and palmettes were common, esp. from the 2nd cent., alongside - and sometimes in combination with - wheel-stamp decorations, incised decorations and painting. ‘Campana B’ black-glaze ware too was sometimes adorned with stamps and fine wheel-stamp decorations; it was manufactured in Etruria from the 2nd quarter of the 2nd cent. to around the mid-1st cent. BC. The stamp decoration of this genre predates that of the Roman Arretine terra sigillata [10. esp. 143-151].</p>
         <p>An independent genre of SW developed from North African terra sigillatain Late Antiquity, known as African Red Slip. Stamps are a typical decorative element from the 4th-7th cents. AD, in the bottoms of open vessels, mostly plates, bowls and platters. Three main phases of this genre can be distinguished. In the first, floral and geometric motifs predominate; the second is dominated by animals and Christian symbols in the centre of large plates and bowls, framed by stamped floral, geometric and animal motifs; the third phase is characterised by decorated crosses, human figures, animals or other motifs [11; 12]. J. W. Hayes distinguished five styles of North African sigillataof Late Antiquity. Recent research has contributed to a better understanding of the working methods of the workshops of this SW [13; 14]. Using the example of the El Mahrine pottery centre in northern Tunisia, M. Mackensen was able to document no fewer than 557 different stamps. Clay stamps have also been published from Sidi Marzouk Tounsi in central Tunisia. A clay plate bearing 23 stamps of 18 different stamp types probably constituted a kind of pattern book. Fine North African SW was distributed far across the Mediterranean region, and inspired much regional production of late Roman SW.</p>
         <p>
                  <ref type="NPOE" target="e1105420">Black-glaze ware</ref>; <ref type="NPOE" target="e900820">Ornaments</ref>; <ref type="NPOE" target="e612820">Pottery, production of</ref>; <ref type="NPOE" target="e1112240">Seals</ref>; <ref type="NPOE" target="e1204690">Terra sigillata</ref>
               </p>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_1_1d1e129">Sparkes, B.A. and Talcott, L.Black and Plain Pottery of the 6th, 5th and 4th Cent.s B.C(Agora1222–311970 B. A. Sparkes, L. Talcott, . ), , 22-31</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_2_1d1e144">Rotroff, S.I. and Pottery, Hellenistic37–381997 S. I. Rotroff, Hellenistic Pottery. Athenian and Imported Wheelmade Tableware and Related Material (Agora 29), , 37-38</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_3_1d1e156">Corbett, P.E.Palmette Stamps from an Attic Black-Glaze1["172-186,", "66-71"]1955 P. E. Corbett, Workshop, in: Hesperia 24, 955, 172-186, Abb. 1 Taf. 66-71</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_4_1d1e168">Morel, J.P.Études de céramique campanienne159–1171969 J. P. Morel, , vol. : L'Atelier des petites estampilles, in: MEFRA 81, , 59-117</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_5_1d1e180">IdLes importations de céramique du IIIe siècle et de la première moitié du IIe siècle. Quelques remarques à propos de l'Ibérie243–246Ramon, J.1998 ., , in: J. Ramon et al. (ed.), Les fàcies ceràmiques d'importació a la Costa Ibèrica, Les Balears i Les Pitiüses durant el segle III aC i la primera meitat del segle II aC, , 243-246</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_6_1d1e199">Sanmartí-Grego, E.El taller de las pequeñas estampillas en la Península Ibérica in: Ampurias 35Abb12164–1711973 E. Sanmartí-Grego, , , 164-171, .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_7_1d1e211">Chelbi, F.Céramique à vernis noir de Carthage41–421992 F. Chelbi, , , 41-42, Taf. 132-138</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_8_1d1e223">Pagenstecher, R.Die calenische Reliefkeramik(JDAI81909–15 R. Pagenstecher, suppl. ), 1909, 15-16</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_9_1d1e235">Morel, J.P.Céramique Campanienne: Les Formes471981 J. P. Morel, , ,</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_10_1d1e247">Lamboglia, N.Per una classificazione preliminare della ceramica campana, in: Atti del Io Congresso Internazionale di Studi Liguri139–2061952 N. Lamboglia, , , 139-206</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_11_1d1e262">Hayes, J.W. and Pottery, Late Roman217–2871972 J. W. Hayes, Late Roman Pottery, , 217-287, 295-296</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_12_1d1e275">IdA Supplement to Late Roman Pottery1980 ., ,</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_13_1d1e284">Mackensen, M.1993 M. Mackensen, Die spätantiken Sigillata- und Lampentöpfereien von El Mahrine (Nordtunesien): Studien zur nordafrikanischen Feinkeramik des 4. bis 7. Jh.,</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="e1122110_bibl_14_1d1e296">Mackensen, M1993 M.Mackensen, NewEvidence for Central Tunisian Red Slip Ware with Stamped Decoration (ARS StyleD), in: Journal of Roman Archaeology11355–3701998  , , 355-370.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
