<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xs="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns:type="application/tei+xml" xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Media</title>
            <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/search?query=local.names+all+%22Ragia M. Effat%22">
               <name type="person">Ragia M. Effat</name>
               <idno type="ORCID"/>
               <idno type="ISNI"/>
            </author>
            <funder ref="placeholder"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>BRILL</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Leiden | Boston</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="placeholder">Placeholder</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Arabic Language and Linguistics</title>
               <editor>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Lutz</forename>
                     <surname>Edzard</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Rudolf</forename>
                     <surname>de Jong</surname>
                  </persName>
               </editor>
               <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
               <idno type="DOI">10.1163/1570-6699_eall_EALL_COM_vol3_0210</idno>
               <idno type="sams-id">eall</idno>
               <idno type="publisher-id">EALO</idno>
               <idno type="ISBN">9789004177024</idno>
               <idno type="ISSN">1570-6699</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p><!-- <info><sumpara>&#x2018;Media&#x2019; (Arabic <hi rend="italic">was&#x0101;&#x02BE;il al-&#x02BE;i&#x02BF;l&#x0101;m</hi>, pl. of <hi rend="italic">was&#x012B;lat al-&#x02BE;i&#x02BF;l&#x0101;m</hi>) is a term for vehicles for the widespread communication to and entertainment of an audience, including printed and electronic means. It is widely agreed that the media are not neutral impassive agencies that transmit news and views, but are themselves influential selectors, shapers, manufacturers, and even, on occasion, fabricators of news and views (McArthur 1998). The topic of this entry is the development of Arabic language media, specifically in Egypt; it discusses journalism, radio, cassette recorders, multichannel television, satellites, new media technology, and the Internet. For the language of the media, <xref target="EALL-">Media Arabic</xref>.</sumpara></info> --></p>
         </abstract>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Language and Linguistics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css" schemeVersion="3.0"/>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="italic">font:italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="bold">font:bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="underline">font:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="subscript">font:subscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="superscript">font:superscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallcaps">font:smallcaps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20090831" status="first-print">Print publication</change>
         <change when="20110530" status="first-online"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">1. Newspapers</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Nasser_President_Gamal_Abdel-05"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Nasser_President_Gamal_Abdel-06"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Sadat_President_Anwar_as--01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Afġānī_Jamāl_ad-Dīn_al--01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Qurān_recitation_of_the-06"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Ṭahṭāwī_Rifāa_Rāfi_aṭ--02"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Mubarak_President_Hosni-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Sayyid_Aḥmad_Luṭfī_as--03"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Abdelfattah_Nabil_MS-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Indo-European_languages-05"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-television_satellite-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-broadcasting_Arabic-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Nadīm_Abdallāh_an--03"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Arabic_broadcasting-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Kamel_Sheikh_Saleh-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Skalička_Vladimir-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-article_definite-59"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-pronoun_relative-28"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Zaborski_Andrzej-08"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Arabic_Egyptian-55"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Rafī_Amīn_ar--01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-relative_pronoun-29"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Abdū_Ibrāhīm-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Abdū_Muḥammad-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Effat_Ragia_M-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Egyptian_Arabic-68"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Amīn_Muṣṭafā-03"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Fleisch_Henri-29"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Kāmil_Muṣṭafā-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-palatalization-16"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Ṣannū_Yaqūb-05"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Arabic_Media-06"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Taqla_Bušārā-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-introflexion-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Media_Arabic-11"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Taqla_Salīm-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Amīn_Alī-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-pan-Arabism-03"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Yūsuf_Alī-01"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-Retsö_Jan-07"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-deixis-02"/>Arabic <anchor xml:id="idx-journalism-05"/>journalism originated in Egypt in 1798. During the French campaign, Arabic pamphlets were distributed instead of the <anchor xml:id="idx-newspapers-13"/>newspapers. The first official newspaper, issued in 1828, was <hi rendition="#italic">al-Waqāʾiʿ al-miṣriyya</hi> ‘The Egyptian proceedings’, edited by Rifāʿ at-Taḥtāwī. <hi rendition="#italic">Al-ʾAhrām</hi> ‘The pyramids’ newspaper was issued by Salīm and Bušārā Taqla in 1875. It has been Egypt's leading newspaper ever since.</p>
         <p>At that time, the newspapers played an important role in politics. ʿAlī Yūsuf issued <hi rendition="#italic">al-Muʾayyid</hi> ‘The supporter’; ʾAḥmad Luṭfī as-Sayyid issued <hi rendition="#italic">al-Garīda</hi> ‘The newspaper’; Muṣṭafā Kāmil issued <hi rendition="#italic">al-Liwāʾ</hi> ‘The banner’; and ʾAmīn ar-Rafʾī issued <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾAxbār</hi> ‘The news’. Humor magazines began to appear, such as <hi rendition="#italic">ʾAbū naḍḍāra</hi> ‘The man with glasses’, issued by Yaʿqūb Ṣanūʿ, and <hi rendition="#italic">at-Tankīt wa-t-tabkīt</hi> ‘Joking and rebuking’ by Nadīm, as a means of criticizing the negative aspects of society.</p>
         <p>In 1884, Jamāl ad-Dīn al-ʾAfġāni and Muḥammad ʿAbdū founded <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʿUrwa al-wut̲qā</hi> ‘The unbreakable bond’. Under British rule, journalism enjoyed a period of relative freedom. However, during World War I, strict <anchor xml:id="idx-censorship-01"/>censorship followed, especially after the event of <anchor xml:id="idx-Dinshaway-01"/>Dinshaway (Al Gindi 1963). After the war, the political parties started to publish their own newspapers in an effort to promote their ideas and principles. The following are some of the more famous newspapers published at that time: <hi rendition="#italic">Ṣawt al-ʾumma</hi> ‘The voice of the nation’, <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾAsās</hi> ‘The basis’, <hi rendition="#italic">Miṣr al-fattāḥ</hi> ‘Victorious Egypt’, <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾIštirākī</hi> ‘The socialist’, <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾIxwān al-muslimūn</hi> ‘The Moslem Brothers’, and <hi rendition="#italic">al-Gamāhir</hi> ‘The public’. The <anchor xml:id="idx-Wafd-01"/>Wafd party owned <hi rendition="#italic">al-Balāġ al-miṣrī</hi> ‘The Egyptian communiqué’. In 1944, <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾAxbār</hi> ‘The news’ and <hi rendition="#italic">ʾAxbār al-yawm</hi> ‘The news of the day’ were published by Muṣṭafā and ʿAlī ʾAmīn.</p>
         <p>In those years, newspapers enjoyed a period of freedom in which they could discuss political and social problems. It was during that time that journalism reached its golden age, especially since martial laws and censorship were abolished (Abdu 1982).</p>
         <p>Nasser's new regime was welcomed by <hi rendition="#italic">al-Miṣrī</hi> ‘The Egyptian’ and <hi rendition="#italic">Rūz al-yūsuf</hi>. However, it was not long before the new regime began to impose hard censorship and abolished the multiparty system. A private Socialist newspaper was established as a voice of the one-party system established by President Nasser. During his rule, Egyptian newspapers became the machine for international misinformation campaigns and falsified stories labeled by Egyptians as <hi rendition="#italic">kalām garāyed</hi> ‘journalistic talk’ (Abdelfattah 1990). When nationalization was declared, all media outlets were placed under the control of the Arab Socialist Union, which set strict guidelines for the press. When multiple political parties were restored under Sadat's regime, the number of daily newspapers and weeklies increased, and many Egyptians consider <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾAhrām</hi> to be the official newspaper of the country.</p>
         <p>The important Egyptian newspapers and magazines are issued by a number of associations: Al Ahram Association issues the daily newspaper <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾAhrām</hi> and the periodicals <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾAhrām al-iqtiṣādī</hi> ‘The economic Ahram’, <hi rendition="#italic">aš-Šabāb wa-l-ʿulūm</hi> ‘Youth and science’, <hi rendition="#italic">al-Mustaqbal</hi> ‘The future’, <hi rendition="#italic">as-Siyāsa ad-dawliyya</hi> ‘International politics’, <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʿArabī</hi> ‘The Arab’, and others.</p>
         <p>Axbar al-Yom Association issues <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾAxbār</hi> ‘The news’, <hi rendition="#italic">ʾAxbār al-yawm</hi> ‘The news of the day’, and <hi rendition="#italic">ʾĀxir sāʿa</hi> ‘The last hour’.</p>
         <p>Dar al-Ma'aref issues <hi rendition="#italic">ʾÚktūbar</hi>. Ros al-Yusuf issues <hi rendition="#italic">Rūz al-yūsuf</hi> and <hi rendition="#italic">Ṣabāḥ al-xayr</hi> ‘Good morning’. Dar al-Tahrir issues <hi rendition="#italic">al-Gumhūriyya</hi> ‘The republic’, <hi rendition="#italic">al-Masāʾ</hi> ‘The evening’, <hi rendition="#italic">ʿAqīdatī</hi> ‘My belief’, and <hi rendition="#italic">Ḥurriyyatī</hi> ‘My freedom’.</p>
         <p>Dar al-Helal issues <hi rendition="#italic">al-Muṣawwar</hi> ‘The illustrated’, <hi rendition="#italic">Hawāʾ</hi> ‘Eve’, <hi rendition="#italic">al-Kawākib</hi> ‘The stars’, and <hi rendition="#italic">al-Hilāl</hi> ‘The crescent’. In addition, each political party issues its own newspaper: <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾAḥrār</hi> ‘The liberals’ (1977), <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾAhālī</hi> ‘The masses’ (1978), <hi rendition="#italic">Māyo</hi> ‘May’ (1981), <hi rendition="#italic">aš-Šaʿb</hi> ‘The people’ (1979), and <hi rendition="#italic">al-Wafd</hi> ‘The delegation’ (1984).</p>
         <p>According to Schleifer (1989), the first major impact of new <anchor xml:id="idx-satellite-03"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-satellite-04"/>satellite technologies on Arab media occurred in the 1980s, not the 1990s, with satellite daily newspapers, not <anchor xml:id="idx-television-15"/>
                  <anchor xml:id="idx-television-16"/>television. First, the <hi rendition="#italic">aš-Šarq al-ʾAwsaṭ</hi> newspaper and later the <hi rendition="#italic">al-Ḥayāt</hi> newspaper began satellite transmissions from London to major population centers throughout the Arab world.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">2. Radio broadcasting</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">2.1 Egyptian broadcasting</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The official opening date of the Marconi-operated Egyptian <anchor xml:id="idx-radio-010"/>radio service was 31 May 1934. The Marconi contract was renewed in 1943. However, anti-British sentiment in the wake of World War II caused the government to cancel the Marconi contract, and the radio service became Egyptian-owned and operated (Youssef 1971). After the formation of the Egyptian Radio Television Federation, control over the electronic media alternated between the Ministry of Information and the Office of the President. Law No. 98 mandated that the language of the service be Arabic (Barrada 1970). However, the service has never broadcast domestically exclusively in Arabic.</p>
         <p>Radio became the voice of the revolution. President Nasser's accomplishments were broadcast to all Arab countries. Nasser, a gifted public speaker, understood the power of the Arabic language and culture. Thus, he profited from this electronic medium to articulate the goals of the revolution. Village peasants and women found themselves sought after as important members of the listening audience. The radio service offered a variety of programs: Radio Cairo, ‘the Main Program’ broadcast, which expanded after July 1952 (Metwally n.d.), offered and continues to offer news, commentary, and various forms of entertainment, the most dominant of which has been drama. Residents of other countries have always been interested in what Egypt's Main Program is saying, especially during times of war. The Main Program is the most listened-to station in the Arab world, following the BBC and Radio Monte Carlo Middle East (RMCME; British Broadcasting Corporation yearly report, 1990). The second ‘Program’ provided the elite with intellectual programs. The Alexandria Local Service was established in 1954 as the first of a series of local services. The People's Program transmissions were intended for illiterate farmers, to promote agricultural advances, literacy training, population planning, and the concept of nationhood (Boyd 1999).</p>
         <p>The Middle East Program (MEP) began in 1959. Nasser's presidential decree established new goals for Egyptian broadcasting: strengthening national feeling, reviving and spreading Arabic culture, encouraging talents, informing foreign countries about the United Arab Republic and the Arab world, and providing entertainment. Of particular importance, MEP allowed broadcast services to accept commercial advertising. This service quickly became popular and an important source of hard currency.</p>
         <p>Egypt's religious service, the Holy Qurʾan Broadcast, was established as an important means of emphasizing the fact that Egypt was an Islamic country, in spite of its close ties with the Soviet Union. It transmitted <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi> recitations and religious discussions.</p>
         <p>Youth Broadcast started in 1975, intending to reach school-age audiences with educational, political, and social messages.</p>
         <p>The Egyptian Palestine Program was devoted to the discussion of the Palestinian problem. After the Egyptian-Israeli Sinai agreement in 1975, the Palestine broadcasts were stopped.</p>
         <p>The Voice of the Arabs is the best known and most widely listened-to regional Arabic radio service. Nasser used this medium to promote his views on Pan-Arabism (Boyd 1999). The Voice of the Arabs was the first major propaganda radio station in the Middle East to have a measurable impact on listeners. It was also used to broadcast to African countries south of the Sahara for the specific purpose of supporting liberation struggles. Since Sadat's assassination, the service has become Egypt's main regional service.</p>
         <p>Radio Cairo's Main Program became domestic in orientation. In April 1981, Egyptian radio was reorganized around seven general network programs: the Main Network, the Local Network, the Qurʾan Network, the Cultural Network, the Voice of the Arabs, the Communication Network, and the Overseas Network (Egyptian Radio and Television Union, 1988). In the 1990s, despite the name changes for some of the services, relatively few major programming changes took place. The new names are the General Program, the Local Network (comprising eleven stations), the Qurʾan Network, the Cultural Network, the Voice of the Arabs, the Middle East Broadcasting Service, and the Foreign Language Service.</p>
         <p>Radio remains an important medium of communication within the Arab world. The majority of the people in the Arab world still depend on radio as a source of entertainment, education, and information. Although the number of illiterate Arabs is decreasing, the overall rate of illiteracy remains very high. Today, Arab listeners no longer need to tune to the transmissions of other Arab countries for news and entertainment. It is also widely believed that television has decreased interest in radio broadc ast.</p>
         <p>Egypt has expanded its international broadcasts. Programs in Arabic are transmitted to Southeast Asia, Latin America, East, Central, and South Africa, and North America (Egyptian Radio and Television Union 1988).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">2.2 International radio broadcasting to Arabic-speaking countries</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union have been significant contributors to the number of Arabic hours transmitted to the Middle East. However, the political and economic changes that have taken place in Eastern Europe since 1989 have negatively affected the number of services using Arabic. For example, Moscow's Radio Peace and Progress, a long-time Arabic broadcaster, ceased operations on 31 May 1991 (British Broadcasting Corporation yearly report, 1991). After English, Arabic is the world's most internationally broadcast language. The Iraqi invasion of Kuwait in August of 1990 and the subsequent Gulf War, along with the deterioration of the Eastern European countries, are two main factors that influenced transmission in Arabic. Since this period, electronic media in the Arab world have been operated by governments. Many Arab world radio listeners tune to foreign stations to learn the international perspective on news and current affairs and to hear programming not generally broadcast by government-operated stations.</p>
         <p>The Arab world was the location of the first effort by the West to broadcast to a developing area for the purpose of attempting to influence people. Beginning in 1934, Italy, through its international radio service BARI, started broadcasting across the Mediterranean in Arabic (Radio Televisione Italiana 1979). Mussolini's radio broadcasts turned increasingly anti-British just after 1935. Britain began studying the possibility of an Arabic service. The BBC hired Egyptian announcers and tried to present appealing radio offerings. Competition arose between Radio BARI and the BBC. In 1939, the Soviet Union and France began broadcasting in Arabic. During the Second World War, the main international broadcasters to the Arab world were Germany and the United Kingdom. The BBC had popular announcers during the war. In his study in the early 1950s, Brunner (1953) mentions the importance of the coffeehouse as a place for listening to radio. There have been numerous major post-World War II events that have tended to increase Arabic broadcasts to the Middle East: the creation of Israel; the 1956 Suez War; the Arab-Israeli conflicts of 1967 and 1973; the increase of the oil price following the October 1973 war; the beginning of the Lebanese civil war in the mid-1970s; President Sadat's trip to Jerusalem in 1977 and his subsequent assassination; the 1982 Israeli invasion of Lebanon and the stationing of United States Marines in Beirut; and the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait in 1990 and the Gulf crisis.</p>
         <p>Western Europe continues to be the leader in Arabic transmission hours. RMCME serves the eastern Arab states and Egypt. Since the 1980s, Radio France International (RFI) has broadcast an Arabic service. It was believed that a popular radio service competing with the Voice of America (VOA) and the BBC would produce closer Arab-French ties. The Radio Monte Carlo Middle East moved in the mid-1970s to the SOFIRAD building in Paris (Regnier 1980). The station has attained an enviable position among rival VOA and BBC broadcasts. Its pro-Arab political orientation influences its popularity.</p>
         <p>Medi 1-Radio Mediterranée Internationale, a private venture between France and Morocco, began broadcasting in Arabic in 1980. Surveys indicate that among the major international services transmitting in Arabic are VOA, BBC, RMCME, Deutsche Welle (1959), and Radio Moscow.</p>
         <p>Dutch Arabic programming by Radio Nederland Wereldomroep started in 1948. Austria, Greece, Italy, Malta, Spain, and Switzerland are minor Arabic broadcasters. Finally, the Austrian radio service started an Arabic service in 1989 (British Broadcasting Corporation yearly report, 1989).</p>
         <p>Iranian Arabic transmission increased after the Iran-Iraq war and during the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait. Cyprus, an active Arabic broadcaster because of its geographic location, increased broadcasts in Arabic during the Lebanese civil war. India, which has a Muslim minority and many expatriate workers in the Arab world, began Arabic broadcasts in 1941. The People's Republic of China started an Arabic service after the 1949 revolution to increase its trade with Arab countries. The Muslim countries of Turkey, Pakistan, Indonesia, and Malaysia have increased their Arabic transmission hours. Four factors – history, trade, politics, and religion – are the major incentives to transmitting in Arabic. Presently, only four countries in North and South America broadcast to the Middle East in Arabic: the United States, Canada, Cuba, and Argentina. The VOA service ranks third, behind RMCME and the BBC, in terms of audience size in the Middle East. The newest North American Arabic service is that of Radio Canada International (RCI).</p>
         <p>In 1964, Nigeria began transmitting in Arabic (Okesanya 1975). Ethiopia has a modest Arabic service, the Radio Voice of the Gospel (RVOG). Djibouti transmits in Arabic because of its Islamic orientation. We should also mention that religious Christian broadcasters wish to reach Christians whose native language is Arabic. New Jersey has the largest religious international radio broadcaster, and Arabic is an important language of Trans World Radio (TWR).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">3. Egyptian television</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In late 1959, a contract was signed between the United Arab Republic and the Radio Corporation of America (RCA) to provide a complete television service for Egypt. It was due to the vision of Nasser that ‘Channel Five’ began transmitting news and programs for development and education. The second program, ‘Channel Nine’, was designed to reach the urban areas. A third channel started in 1960 but was closed after 1967. The end of the war of 1967 saw a decrease of foreign programming. More importance was given to nationalistic, educational, and religious topics. However, the quality of Egyptian TV programs declined between 1967 and 1974. President Nasser signed a decree establishing the Egyptian Radio-Television Federation. Television in Egypt is owned by the state. The national television channels were extensions of the Ministry of Information.</p>
         <p>More than any other mass media, television tended to reflect the changing international political orientation of the country. During the Egyptian-Israeli war of 1973, the Egyptian media took a very different attitude than they had during and after the 1967 war. Radio tended to be more honest and less confident about the victory when the Suez Canal was crossed. Television reflected the happiness of the Egyptians after 1973. With Sadat's declaration of an open-door policy, British and American programs increased on Egyptian television. The income of advertisement and commercials and the revenue from exporting Arabic programs to other countries increased significantly. Since the 1980s, the Egyptian television became the most important outlet to advertize a variety of goods and services (Egyptian Radio and Television Union 1988). The system of Egyptian Radio and Television Union (ERTU) is the most influential in the Arab world. Arab countries have generally relied on Egyptian media production for television programming such as drama series, variety programs, talk shows, and films. The ‘Voice of Cairo’ was established to become involved in production and distribution in the Arab world, and has become an important source of hard currency. After Egypt's peace treaty with Israel, some countries decreased or stopped altogether the purchase of Egyptian TV programs: Lebanon, South Yemen, Libya, Syria, and Iraq.</p>
         <p>The weekly magazine <hi rendition="#italic">al-ʾIḏāʿa wa-t-tilivizyūn</hi> was first issued in 1935 under the name of <hi rendition="#italic">ar-Rādiyū al-miṣrī</hi> to provide articles about broadcasting figures, features of the various aspects of the broadcast media, and a detailed television and radio schedule. During the period from 1981 to 1992, several factors contributed to the development and expansion of Egyptian television: A third channel was established. Currency restrictions on the import of goods were lifted. The death in October 1983 of President Anwar Sadat and the evolution of Egypt as part of the Arab world have contributed to the confidence building of Egyptian television and greatly added to the attractiveness of Egyptian video products. The Lebanese civil war ended Lebanon's competition with Egyptian program exports. President Mubarak gave more room for free expression in news, films, and television series.</p>
         <p>Television has become the main source of entertainment over information at home or in the local coffee shop. For many lower-income people, a television set is more important than a refrigerator. With the spread of digital multichannel satellite platforms, the impact of television in this decade has exploded.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">4. Videocassette recorders</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Egyptians working outside the country brought home to their families television sets and <anchor xml:id="idx-videocassette-01"/>videocassettes. Videocassette recorders are widely used in Egyptian urban and rural areas by viewers who want to have a choice in what they watch. Both Egyptian and Western films are widely available in rental stores and shops.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">5. Satellite television</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Satellite distribution has offered new opportunities to Egypt. The ARABSAT system has made it possible for television systems in the Middle East to rebroadcast Egyptian television live. Beginning in 1990, Egypt began offering via satellite connection rebroadcasts of the Egyptian main service. In late 1990, Bahrain permitted limited rebroadcasting of Egyptian television. For a time following the 1991 Gulf War, Egyptian television was used in place of Kuwaiti television. In 1992, the Egyptian government legalized the import and ownership of dishes.</p>
         <p>Tapes of Egyptian television programming are part of virtually every Middle East television system. Satellite distribution has presented Egypt with new opportunities. Egypt's stock of films and television productions and ARABSAT-leased transponders make this technically possible. NILESAT was inaugurated in May 1995, providing specialized educational, cultural, family, children, religious, health, sports, drama, and other programming. It allows the rebroadcast of all Egyptian television and radio services, as well as national channels from other Arab countries. The activation of Egypt's NILESAT direct broadcast service makes it clear that the Egyptian government will continue to invest in television and radio production and delivery systems to maintain its historical dominance of Arab-world electronic media (Boyd 1999).</p>
         <p>In 1989 CNN began to rebroadcast terrestrially, a pay-TV operation that came to be known as CNE (Cable Network Egypt) Cairo. MultiChoice Egypt now administers a subscription management service and holds a small minority share in CNE Cairo.</p>
         <p>The Egyptian Space Net (ESN) began to broadcast thirteen hours of daily programming. After the Gulf War, dish ownership was further stimulated because of a decline in the price of satellite dishes, wider international programming, and an increase in the number of companies marketing, servicing, and even manufacturing dishes. Television broadcasting directly to receivers in and to the Arab world via satellite became possible. The first of these satellite systems was the Middle East Broadcasting Centre (MBC), which began transmission and production in London in September 1991. It broadcasts eighteen hours a day, providing a mix of news, sports, fashions, movies, and general entertainment.</p>
         <p>The second private Arab satellite system – and the largest in reach and in Arabic programming – is Arab Radio and Television (ART), established by Sheikh Saleh Kamel. It began transmission via ARABSAT from Cairo in January 1994. ART started separate channels for movies, sports, and children's programming, as well as a general channel. Since then, ART has become a global platform for more than twenty channels, besides live and syndicated sports coverage. By mid-1997 ART offered six satellite program services. In its quest for quality, ART has increased the number of public shows which involve audience participation and tackle controversial and daring social issues, such as divorce, premarital sex, male impotence, and drug use (Schleifer 1998).</p>
         <p>The most recent Arab satellite system to come onto the scene is Orbit, launched in May 1994 and transmitted from Rome. Orbit's Arabic programming is more or less confined to <hi rendition="#italic">at̲-Ṭāniya</hi>, an Arabic-language general channel with some of the most successful entertainment and public affairs programming on the air. Orbit challenged MBC's strong card – an Arabic-language news service that provided field reporting at an international standard beyond comparison to propagandistic tendencies of the Arab world's national channels. Orbit made a contract with the BBC to produce a BBC Arabic World Television Service, which was offered exclusively in the Orbit package. It is an independent and credible news source in the Arab world. Orbit began transmitting an Arabic version of the BBC World Service with full editorial control remaining in the hands of the BBC – in other words, in the hands of non-Arabs.</p>
         <p>When the BBC Arabic TV Service began in June 1994, it appeared to overwhelm MBC; however, the relative indifference to Arab cultural values on the part of many BBC executives, combined with often culturally irrelevant programming, troubled many Arab viewers. Thus, Orbit's management was obliged to break its contract with the BBC in 1996. MBC distinguished itself by following the international format; newsworthiness rather than government press releases determined the line-up and news stories were scripted to picture rather than to an anchor reading wire copy. MBC's style was also unique because, in contrast to the BBC Arabic service, it retained the more cautious approach (Schleifer 1998).</p>
         <p>MBC's chief problem is that it is no longer alone. <anchor xml:id="idx-Al-Jazeera-04"/>Al-Jazeera, the all-news Arabic-language channel transmitted via satellite from Qatar, employs many of the former Arabic-speaking broadcasters from the BBC venture. The other competitors include the Arab News Network (ANN), Abu Dhabi, Dubai, LBC, El Arabia, and the Egyptian channels.</p>
         <p>As for Orbit, it has gained from the BBC experience to increase the amount of original Arabic programming by dramatically expanding its own production facilities in Cairo, Beirut, and the Gulf.</p>
         <p>Arabic satellite programming – Arab in its cultural authenticity – has dramatically stimulated the sale of dishes. With the increasing availability of dishes, Islamic society in general, and Arab society in particular, is proud of the use of Classical Arabic and the media-prevalent Modern Standard Arabic. However, there is a concern about what is shocking to Arab conventions and against Islamic principles and ethical, moral, and social values. The first political danger is the fear of reaction of anti-Western, Islamic fundamentalism to the sudden easy availability of disorienting, subversive cultural materials of Western television programming via Direct Broadcast Satellite (DBS)/Direct To Home (DTH) satellite transmission. The second political concern has to do with government sensitivity to unfavorable news reporting by satellite stations. The third political concern is the possibility of satellite broadcasts from hostile countries.</p>
         <p>By the mid-1990s, DTH television had become a fact of life, with widespread dish ownership throughout the region, particularly in the Gulf. DTH satellite transmission has become increasingly popular in Egypt. The increasing popularity of satellite television and the wide variety of choices have led some to question whether there should be some control over what is transmitted. Programs span all fields of knowledge: scientific, political, economic, cultural, religious, and educational, as well as entertainment programs.</p>
         <p>Egypt has always been a pioneer in media production in the Middle East. Egypt is very keen to preserve the Arabic culture and to spread it to native and non-native speakers of Arabic. Satellite makes it possible for <ref target="EALL-SIM-vol3-0087">Media Arabic</ref> to reach all parts of the world. Thus, the challenge for Egypt lies in upgrading and expanding its own television product, whether news or entertainment, so that it can ensure its cultural sovereignty in a globally competitive situation. Egypt, alone among the Arab states, has the depth of talent for such an undertaking. It has scores of actors, singers, dancers, musicians, comedians, journalists, producers, directors, and even <hi rendition="#italic">Qurʾān</hi> reciters. In addition, Egyptian colloquial Arabic is universally understood throughout the Arab world due to the spread of Egyptian films.</p>
         <p>Al-Mehwar, Nile News, and Nile TV are news channels that broadcast from Egypt. They provide something different than most of the news channels in the Gulf region. They represent the essence of Egyptian life from a news angle with a comprehensive concept of news, not just political news but also business news, cultural news, sports, and fashion. Egypt is a different culture, a different civilization, a different political situation. Egypt is the most populated country in the region, with the longest history, and many people across the region are interested in it.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rendition="#bold">6. Conclusion</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Nowadays, the influence of the print media has declined in the face of technological advances. The televised media have now adapted the print media and blended it with visual and vocal material. In the 21st century, it is not the print news media but the space and terrestrial channels of the television, as well as the <anchor xml:id="idx-Internet-07"/>Internet, that have the greater influence in the trends of international and public opinion.</p>
         <p>New media technology, from cassette recorders to multichannel television, mobile phones, and even the Internet, afford wider circulation to communications to a highly educated generation. The new generation has unprecedented opportunities for participation in media, and receptor models changed to be more interactive ones.</p>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_1_1d1e501">Abdelfattah, NabilLinguistic changes in journalistic language in Egypt, 1937–1997: A quantitative and comparative analysis1990. . . Ph.D. diss., University of Texas at Austin.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_2_1d1e510">Abdu, IbrahimEgyptian press development1982Cairo: Association of Arab Register</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_3_1d1e519">Abu-Lughod, Ibrahim. 1963The mass media and Egyptian village lifeSocial Forces42–97. “”. 42.97–104.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Al_Gindi_Anwar-01">Gindi, Al and AnwarThe Arabic language between supporters and opponents1963CairoAnglo BookshopAl Gindi, Anwar. . . : .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_5_1d1e539">Union, Arab States BroadcastingThe United Arab Republic: TV1969ASBU, Cairo. [MimeographedArab States Broadcasting Union. . “”. .]</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_6_1d1e546">Badawī, as-SaʿīdMustawayāt al-luġa al-ʿarabiyya al-muʿāṣira fī Miṣr1973CairoDāral-Maʿārif. . . : al-Maʿārif.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Barrada_F-01">Barrada, F.The history of the U.A.R. radio since its establishment in 1934 till now1970 . “”. Arab Broadcasts 63–70. [Transl. from Arabic.]</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Boyd_Douglas_A-01">Boyd, Douglas A.Broadcasting in the Arab world: A survey of the electronic media in the Middle East1999AmesIowa State University Press</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_9_1d1e579">Corporation, British BroadcastingBBC handbook1980LondonBritish Broadcasting Corporation. . . : British Broadcasting Corporation.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Brunner_Edmund-01">Brunner, EdmundRural communications: Behavior and attitudes in the Middle EastRural Sociology18–1491953. . “”. 18.149–155.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_11_1d1e599">Radio, Egyptian and Union, TelevisionEgyptian Radio and Television Union in briefCairo: Egyptian Radio and Television Union1988Egyptian Radio and Television Union. . . .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_12_1d1e609">Glubb, John BagotBritain and the Arabs1959LondonHodder and Stoughton</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_13_1d1e618">Hamza, AbdellateefLiterature and the press. Cairo: Dār al-Fikr al-ʿArabī1961</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-McArthur_Tom-01">McArthur, TomThe concise Oxford companion to the English language1998Oxford: Oxford University Press</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_15_1d1e638">Metwally, E.A.Nd“Historical survey of the Egyptian Broadcast with background of the pre-revolution period”. Egyptian Radio Television FederationCairoMimeographedMetwally, E.A. N.d. , . [.]</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Okesanya_Ayo-01">Okesanya, AyoNigerian Broadcasting Corporation1975Lagos</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="EALL-COM-vol3-0210_bibl_17_1d1e655">Italiana, Radio Televisione1979RomeRadio Televisione Italiana. . .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Regnier_Jean_Pierre-01">Regnier, Jean Pierre1980Paris. . Radio Monte Carlo Middle East. .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Schleifer_Abdallah_S-01">Schleifer, Abdallah S.Transnational broadcasting studies. Cairo: Adham Center for Television and Journalism and The1998 . American University in Cairo.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="idx-Youssef_F-01">Youssef, F.What do you know about Egyptian broadcasting?1971 . “” Arab Broadcasts 63–77. [Transl. from Arabic.]</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
