<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xs="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns:type="application/tei+xml" xml:id="COM-00013">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Anarchism</title>
            <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/search?query=local.names+all+%22Ulrich Bröckling%22">
               <name type="person">Ulrich Bröckling</name>
               <idno type="ORCID"/>
               <idno type="ISNI"/>
            </author>
            <funder ref="placeholder"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>BRILL</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Leiden | Boston</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="placeholder">Placeholder</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">The Brill Dictionary of Religion</title>
               <editor>
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Kocku</forename>
                     <surname>von Stuckrad</surname>
                  </persName>
               </editor>
               <biblScope unit="volume"/>
               <biblScope unit="page">55</biblScope>
               <idno type="DOI">10.1163/1872-5287_bdr_COM_00013</idno>
               <idno type="sams-id">bdr</idno>
               <idno type="publisher-id">BDRO</idno>
               <idno type="ISBN">9789004124332</idno>
               <idno type="ISSN">1872-5287</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Religious Studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css" schemeVersion="3.0"/>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="italic">font:italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="bold">font:bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="underline">font:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="subscript">font:subscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="superscript">font:superscript;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallcaps">font:smallcaps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20051223" status="first-print">Print publication</change>
         <change when="20060919" status="first-online"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
                  <head>
                     <hi rendition="#italic">Rule without State</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>1. Walter Benjamin's celebrated statement—that there has been no radical concept of freedom in Europe since Bakunin (1814–1876)—goes to the heart of anarchistic theory and praxis: anarchism is a freedom movement. Its goal is social order without the rule of human beings by human beings. Like the other revolutionary currents of the nineteenth and twentieth century, anarchism, too, seized on the emancipation of the middle class and the thinking of the  Enlightenment, and proposed to go beyond them radically. Of course, while the Social Democratic and Communist Party component of the labor movement inscribed its banner with conquest of political power, the anarchists struggled with the state as the most powerful amassment of organized force. It was to be replaced by free association: a network of voluntary, always terminable, agreements, among sovereign individuals and groups. The goal of (Gk.) ‘an-archism’—the absence of rule—corresponded to an <hi rendition="#italic">anthropological optimism</hi>: only let the organs of oppression and ideologies of authority be dismantled, anarchists were convinced, and human beings would regulate their relationships in spontaneous solidarity. Not only the state, but every form of organized compulsion came under anarchist fire, especially religious dogmas and the system of capitalistic wage-earning. A closed canon of anarchist doctrines is of course nonexistent—it would be a self-contradiction—rather, anarchism comes forward as a heterogeneous, direction-switching movement, between individualism and collectivism, nonviolent and militant, destructive and constructive, unified only by its single goal of the complete dismantling of the state. The rejection of ecclesiastical and civil authority alike ultimately bespeaks an ideal of equality and siblingship, to be realized in a communistic community of goods. Thus, anarchists are at home in bohemian enclaves as in radical union organizations, settlements and communes, just as they are in secret societies that bind themselves by oath. It was not in appeals and petitions, nor in parliamentary participation, that the anarchists placed their hopes for society's deliverance, but in direct action and egalitarian organizing. It was a resounding voluntarism of praxis that begat the moral pathos of anarchistic writings: when all is said and done, everything is to depend on the decision of the individual to join forces in revolutionary association with those of the same mind, and to organize the disintegration of power.</p>
               </div>
         <div>
                  <head>
                     <hi rendition="#italic">Critique of Religion and Christian Anarchism</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>2. a) The anarchist <hi rendition="#italic">critique of religion</hi>, formulated most sharply in Mikhail Bakunin's <hi rendition="#italic">God and the State</hi> (1871), attacked religious convictions as a ‘renunciation of human reason,’ and the ‘most decisive rejection of human freedom’—and thereupon concluded, “If God did exist, He would have to be eliminated.”</p>
                  <p>b) Leo N. Tolstoy's (1828–1910) social ethics is frequently denoted a ‘Christian anarchism.’ Tolstoy began with an understanding of Christianity strictly oriented to the Sermon on the Mount, to conclude on a wholesale condemnation of any application of force, and therefore called for disobedience to civil laws, especially to military conscription. Hope for a revolutionary overthrow of the state power structure, of course, was self-deception in the eyes of the social philosopher, as violent rebellion could only reproduce evil, and further spin the spiral of violence. Deliverance from the cycle could be attained only through inner change, and rejection of all un-Christian demands of the state, especially of that of military service. Tolstoy's postulate of universal freedom from physical constraint, however, stood in sharp opposition not only to doctrines of the state, but to the social teachings of the Christian churches, as well.</p>
                  <p>c) Notwithstanding the thrust of its thoroughgoing anticlerical and preponderantly atheistic route, the anarchist movement exhibits parallels to Ernst Troelsch's ‘sect type’ category in his sociology of religion. After all, like the religious sects, anarchist ‘free association’ is likewise a ‘community of volunteers in conscious connection,’ and thereby the contrary image of an ‘institutional’ organization type. In anarchism's implicit anthropology, we witness the return, in secular form, of the doctrine of the ‘primordial condition’ of an ‘unspoiled nature,’ a nature without violence, compulsion, law, war, power, or private property ( Garden/Paradise; Utopia).<note n="1">
                        T<hi rendition="#smallcaps">roeltsch</hi> 1912, 372, 379.
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </div>
         <div>
                  <head>
                     <hi rendition="#italic">Historical Development</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>3. The first to denominate himself an ‘anarchist’ was Pierre Joseph Proudhon (1809–1865). In his writings he advocated a type of federative community organization (mutualism) that would be erected on just and fair laws of exchange. Ecclesiastical and civil authority alike would necessarily collapse, in his conviction, if income corresponded to time expended, and income without work were excluded. Under the influence of Mikhail Bakunin, anarchism developed into a movement of social revolution. Beginning in the 1860s, in sharp differentiation from the ‘authoritarian state capitalism’ of Marx and Engels, Bakunin propagated the concept of collectivist anarchism. Means of production, capital, and land ought to be transferred to the ownership of workers' associations, organized as federations, and the right to inheritance should be abolished. Bakunin rejected any political activity on the part of the proletariat, especially participation in elections, and called for the seizure of the means of production, and the destruction of political power, in a social revolution. Peter Kropotkin (1842–1921) countered Proudhon's call to a full work output with the principle, “To each according to his needs, from each according to his capacity.” Kropotkin's writings amalgamated scientists' conviction of the reality of progress with a backward-looking idealization of the medieval guilds or Russian village communities. To him, these constituted a model of the coming free society.</p>
                  <p>After 1880, the anarchist movement was gradually sidetracked, owing not least of all to a series of successful and attempted assassinations, and the accompanying state harassment. Only its alliance with the unionizing component of the labor movement brought a new heyday. The anarchists attained their greatest historical influence in Spain, where, after the 1936 revolution, they undertook short-lived attempts to create free-communist social organizations. Anarchistic ideas were revived, at times with an explicit appeal to historical roots, in the anti-authoritarian student movement of 1968, as in the alternative movements of the 1970s and 1980s.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <hi rendition="#italic">
                        <ref target="COM-00097">Conflict</ref>, <ref target="COM-00104">Criticism of Religion</ref>, <ref target="COM-00189">Group</ref>, <ref target="COM-00187">Government/Rule/Politics/State</ref>, <ref target="COM-00470">Utopia</ref>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>
                     Literature
                  </head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_1_1d1e126">Bakunin, Mikhail, Selected Writings, ed. by Arthur Lehning, New York 1973</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_2_1d1e138">Bakunin, Mikhail, Statism and Anarchy, ed. by Marshall S. Shatz, New York 1990</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_3_1d1e147">Bakunin, Mikhail, The Basic Bakunin, ed. by Robert M. Cutler, Buffalo 1996</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_4_1d1e156">Carter, April, The Political Theory of Anarchism, London 1971</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_5_1d1e166">Crowder, George, Classical Anarchism: The Political Thought of Godwin, Proudhon, Bakunin, and Kropotkin, Oxford/New York 1991</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_6_1d1e175">Guérin, Daniel, Anarchism: From Theory to Practice, New York 1970 (Fr. 1965)</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_7_1d1e184">Heider, Ulrike, Anarchism: Left, Right, and Green, San Francisco 1994</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_8_1d1e193">Joll, James, The Anarchists, London 1980</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_9_1d1e202">Lehning, Arthur, From Buonarroti to Bakunin, Leiden 1970</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_10_1d1e211">May, Todd, The Political Philosophy of Poststructuralist Anarchism, University Park 1994</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_11_1d1e221">Nettlau, Max, Anarchy Through the Times, New York 1979</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_12_1d1e230">Newman, Saul, From Bakunin to Lacan: Anti-Authoriarianism and the Dislocation of Power, Lanham 2001</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="COM-00013_bibl_13_1d1e239">Troeltsch, Ernst, The Social Teaching of the Christian Churches, Chicago 1981 (Ger. 1912).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
